<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints solace: or, The condition, and consolation of the saints in the earth Deliuered in certaine sermons at Eatonbridge in Kent. By the minister there.</title>
            <title>Saints solace</title>
            <author>Bostock, Peter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 166 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 123 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3395</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117350</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852565</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17891</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16479)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17891)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1227:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints solace: or, The condition, and consolation of the saints in the earth Deliuered in certaine sermons at Eatonbridge in Kent. By the minister there.</title>
                  <title>Saints solace</title>
                  <author>Bostock, Peter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 234 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Hauiland for Robert Bostocke, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Kings head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Peter Bostock.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17891:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17891:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS SOLACE: OR, The Condition, And Conſolation Of <hi>The Saints in the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Deliuered in certaine Sermons at <hi>Eatonbridge</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Miniſter there.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 94.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In the multitude of the ſorrowes that I had in my heart: thy comforts haue refreſhed my ſoule.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Hauiland</hi> for <hi>Robert Boſtocke,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Kings head. 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:17891:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17891:2"/>
            <head>TO The right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull, Sir <hi>Robert Heath</hi> Knight, his Maieſties Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall: Grace and all good bleſſings from God the Father, and our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat <hi>the Elders of the Iewes</hi> vnto Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of the Centurious loue <hi>vnto their Nation</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luk 7.5.</note> might bee ſaid vnto all, of your loue
<pb facs="tcp:17891:3"/> and care of our <hi>Eaton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge;</hi> where by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme you were initiated, and whereof the ſpirituall <hi>wealth</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eſth. 10.3</note>, you haue earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſought, both by your owne bountie, and other annuall penſions procured by you, from your worthy friends *, and worſhipfull alliance in the adiacent parts, vnto the Miniſter, which ſhould bee there reſident, to <hi>edifie</hi> the people on the <hi>moſt holy faith.</hi> It is not to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of any, how you began to honour God, whew he began to honour you, and how hee hath gone on, in honouring you, as you haue him: If
<pb facs="tcp:17891:3"/> any ſhould, I cannot, nor will forget your great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe extended towards me (of all the Lords ſeruants the leaſt and vnworthieſt) ſince you firſt ſaw me: your counſell, countenance, and encouragement after my firſt entrance into that <hi>Cure,</hi> (now eleuen yeares paſt:) and lately your power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand ſtretched out, in the happie ſtrength thereof, to ſaue mee from the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of them that would haue<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 57.3.</note> ſwallowed mee vp; are (if I would ingratefully be ſilent) moſt euident teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding world. And yet vnto
<pb facs="tcp:17891:4"/> all theſe (as if all theſe were ſmall in your ſight) it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed you afterwards to adde other fauours, when you tooke me to your houſe, and ſent mee home, not emptie, but full of comfort and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage in the worke of the Miniſterie, for the time to come. As <hi>Dauid</hi> vnto the Lord, I might ſay vnto you; <hi>Is this the manner of man</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Sam. 7.19.</note>? <hi>What ſhall I render vnto you, for all your benefits towards mee?</hi> My ſelfe I owe you, and ſuch as <hi>I haue giue I you;</hi> Theſe few impoliſhed papers: But what are theſe? of which the acceptation
<pb facs="tcp:17891:4"/> will be the augmentation of my debt: or why theſe, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than ſome other of my labours is that place, which ſome haply iudge (if I would needs to it) more worthy the preſſe? <hi>Nothing but preſſure (God is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) brought me to the preſſe:</hi> and theſe (being mine immediate Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after the Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of my <hi>terrible trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> and the fruits of thoſe ſorrowes, or ſorrowfull thoughts, which were then, in my ſoule) would (as I thought) vnto the people of God be acceptable; as is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God himſelfe; the <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:17891:5"/> ſpirit, the broken and contrite heart</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 51.17</note>.</p>
            <p>Nothing elſe, Right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull but theſe rude lines, (which, in the dayes of my trouble, I found by enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in <hi>the Sanctuarie of God,</hi> or otherwiſe by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, meditation, obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and experience,) haue I <hi>(Me penes)</hi> to preſent vnto you: but for you, and your honoured family, <hi>all prayers and ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the ſpirit,</hi> I will (as my daily ſacrifice) offer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>golden altar</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Reuel 8.3.</note>, vnto him who <hi>regardeth,</hi> and <hi>deſpiſeth not the prayer of the deſtitute</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 109.17</note>. The
<pb facs="tcp:17891:5"/> Lord bleſſed you and aſsiſt you in your high calling: The Lord giue you the price of that other <hi>high calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 3.14</note>, for which with all Saints you <hi>preſſe vnto the mark: The Lord make you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in Bethlehem, and alwayes to doe worthily in Ephratah</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ruth. 4.11</note>. <hi>The Lord increaſe you more and more: you and your children. Bleſſed bee yee of the Lord which made Heauen and earth</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 115.14, 15.</note>. Thus recommending this little booke, with my ſelfe the poore Author thereof, vnto your implored Patronage
<pb facs="tcp:17891:6"/> and Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ection, I craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for my boldneſſe, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worſhips euer, and in all dutie bounden,</hi> Peter Boſtock.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Eatonbridge,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Iune 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>.</hi> Anno Salutis, <hi>1630.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17891:6"/>
            <head>THE SAINTS SOLACE: OR Comforts for Afflicted.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 119. VER. 50.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>This is my comfort in my affliction.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Booke of Pſalmes a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon promptit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie of Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine;<note place="margin">Commune quoddam Medicina promptua. arium. Ambr.</note> many authorities
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17891:7"/> out of it in the booke of Ieſus Chriſt, a Law in which his delight was, and his Diſciples exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, what other ſong in the houſe of their Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, or reioycing, the Saints together, what other Odes vſed? All ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable, but<note n="a" place="margin">Ambr. Hic pſah<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us tribus in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus on nibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntecellit: <hi>1.</hi> Vtilitate. <hi>2.</hi> Longitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine. 3. Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantia &amp; artificio al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabetico. Bellar in tit. b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius pſal.</note> as the Suns the Moones light, this ſurpaſſeth all. The ſong of ſongs which was <hi>Dauids;</hi> indited for mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter accurately,<note n="b" place="margin">Muſcubus. Wilcos. ibid.</note> compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for memorie exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely, many prayers to God, many praiſes of his Word, many profeſſions of obedience compriſed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17891:7"/> therein; Octonaries 22. the parts thereof, euery verſe of the 8. in euerie one, beginning in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew with one letter, this Section with <hi>Zaiin</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Zaiin quaſi Ziu, i. telum, quod claua figura eſſe vidcatur.</note> a club in figure, in ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation a weapon, defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue, and offenſiue for vſe. <hi>A defence,</hi> to them that decline not from the Law of God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>vid v.</hi> 51, 52, 53, 54, 55, 56,</note> but remember his Name, his Word, his Iudgements of old, his Statutes and Precepts to keepe the ſame. <hi>An of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> to the proud that haue the humble in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and to the wicked that forſake the Law.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17891:8"/> What other myſterie bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the letter for the vſe of edifying? As other haue laboured with that in <hi>Thren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in Thren. Ier.</note> we might with the Alphabeticall artifice here; but comfort in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction being <hi>(vnum il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud)</hi> that one thing which we ſeeke, we will ſet our heart on that one thing, and giue our ſelues whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereunto.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">D. King Epiſs. Lond. lect. in Ion.</note> The World a Sea in a Similitude, ſwelling with pride, and vainglorie, the wind to heaue it vp, blew, and huid with enuy; boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with wrath, deepe with couetouſneſſe, fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17891:8"/> with luxuriouſnes, ſwallowing, and drinking in all by oppreſſions, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerfull for the Rockes of preſumption and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, riſing with, the waues of paſſions &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations, ebbing and flowing with lightneſſe, and inconſtancy, briniſh &amp; ſalt with iniquitie, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and vnſauourie with all kinde of miſerie.</p>
            <p>The confeſſion in the Text of an expert Naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gator, as the light in the Admirall, by which ſo many as ſaile after him, through that vaſt, turbid, belluous, and circumflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17891:9"/> Ocean: may for the ſtrengthning of their ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke Soules, behold</p>
            <p>His
<list>
                  <item>Condition, Affliction</item>
                  <item>and Conſolation, The Word.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. His Condition or ſtate of life ſeaſoned with Affliction. Afflicted hee was greatly,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 116.10.</note> and would bee remembred with all his afflictions,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſa. 132.1.</note> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars inducted, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.102. and this 119.<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 119.23.61 69.85 86, 87. Pſal 102.3, 4.8. Verſ. 23 Verſ. 78. Verſ. 61.</note> the princes, the powers, the proud, the wicked com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined againſt him, yea, ſworne againſt him, and mad againſt him;<note place="margin">Verſ. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> what lies ſorged they? what
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17891:9"/> pits digged they?<note place="margin">Verſ. 84.</note> perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wrongfully,<note place="margin">Verſ. 36.</note> conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med on the earth,<note place="margin">Verſ. 87.</note> waited for to be deſtroyed,<note place="margin">Verſ. 95.</note> hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with dogs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 22.16.</note> their feet ſwift, their mouths deepe as wide, and their teeth as ſharpe, compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with many bulls,<note place="margin">Verſ. 10.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet round with ſtrong bulls, incloſed with the aſſemblies of the wicked;<note place="margin">Verſ. 16.</note> gaped on with their mouthes,<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> laughed to ſcorne,<note place="margin">Verſ. 7</note> ſmitten with their tongues,<note place="margin">Pſal. 52.2, 3, 4. &amp; 120 3, 4.</note> their tongues as ſpeares and razors, and words as ſwords, powred out li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e water, all his bones ſundred, his heart
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17891:10"/> like wax melting in the midſt of his bowels,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.14.</note> his ſtrength dried vp like a potſheard,<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note> the reproach of men,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> yea, a worme and no man, caſt out and brought into the duſt of death.<note place="margin">Verſ. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>Maruell not that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> the ſeruant of the Lord, ſound faithfull as <hi>Moſes</hi> in all his houſe, a man after his owne heart, which fulfilled all his will;<note place="margin">Acts 13.22</note> Beloued as his name ſounds, and beloued of the Lord, was exerciſed with ſuch anxious and crieuous afflictions, for <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17891:10"/>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>i.</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, the elect of God are all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted as <hi>Dauid</hi> was, and called all <hi>Iedid</hi> his belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 127.2.</note>; yet none exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the ſufferings of the preſent time, no not one, not one amongſt the excellent from <hi>Adam</hi> to Chriſt, &amp; from Chriſt to this our day, that hath not in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure taſted of the cup which is full of mixture,<note n="f" place="margin">Iude v.3.</note> common as the ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the grace of God which bringeth ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> tentation, and tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.<note n="g" place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.6.</note> The <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> receiued the word
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17891:11"/> with much affliction.<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 10.32</note> The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned indured a great fight of afflictions.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note>The whole houſhold of faith, all the fellow citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, all that liue godly, all the ſons of God, all the children of light, all that hold forth the word of life, are in this life par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of afflictions. Thus I might conclude.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Obiect.</hi> But this doore opened, ſome will op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on this wiſe: Hard is this ſaying to the Non-afflicted, that enioy this worlds ioy, proſperity
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17891:11"/> and peace; for being without any manner of affliction, whereof all are partakers that are<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 12 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſons, elect, beloued, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, are they not Sp. hated, reiected, reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as <hi>Edom,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Mal. 1.2, 3, 4.</note> &amp; reſerued as the wicked to the day of deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Carnall the peace altogether and without truth, or pride and ſecurity the fruit thereof with hardneſſe of heart, it's (as the proſperitie of fooles) a bleſſing curſed, and the <hi>praeludium</hi> to deſtruction.<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 92.6</note> 
               <hi>A brutiſh man knoweth
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17891:12"/> not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note> 
               <hi>neither doth a foole vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this;</hi> but the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſpeaketh expreſly, <hi>When the wicked ſpring as the graſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 92 7.</note> 
               <hi>and when all the workers of iniquity flouriſh, it is, that they ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for euer.</hi> Take for example the two notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fooles,<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 25</note> the one, the man of <hi>Maon,</hi> whoſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions were in <hi>Carmel,</hi> a very great man, hauing three thouſand ſheepe, and one thouſand goats, and liuing in proſperity, yet ſmitten in a moment, his heart died within him, and he became as a ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne;<note n="o" place="margin">Luc. 12.19.</note> the other, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17891:12"/> man in the parable, who, when his ground brought forth plentifully, wanted roome where to beſtow his fruits, would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore inlarge his barnes, and hauing therein laid vp much goods for many years, ſing without grace <hi>requiem</hi> to his ſoule; <hi>Soule take thine eaſe, eat, drinke, and be merry;</hi> but the ſame night <hi>his ſoule was required of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contrà, this I ſay and teſtifie in the Lord,</hi> that outward peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity had, with the peace of God, and of conſcience, (the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17891:13"/> of God firſt ſought and found, with his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, its the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Lord without affliction or ſorrow ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with it<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 10.22.</note>. Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> prayer for <hi>Gaius</hi> was, that he might proſper and be in health as his ſoule pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered.<note n="q" place="margin">Io. ep. 3. 2.</note> A man beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing himſelfe wiſely in a perfect way, walking within his houſe with a perfect heart,<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 102.2. Gen. 17.2. Micah. 6.7.</note> vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before God, humbly with him, doing iuſtly, louing mercy, caſting on the waters, diſperſing, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to the poore, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17891:13"/> of others in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, if peace &amp; truth be with him in his dayes, its the face of God ſhining on him, the light of his countenance, and the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence of his proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, how otherwiſe ſhould the poore affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted bee releeued, and their ſoules ſuſtained?<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Reg. 18.13.</note> 
               <hi>Obadiah</hi> not in caſe to doe it, who ſhall hide the Prophets in a caue, and feed them with bread and water? <hi>Nehemiah</hi> not in fauor with <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Neh. 4 2, 3, 4, &amp;c.</note> who ſhall procure any fauour to <hi>Ieruſalem? Oneſiphorus,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.16. Philo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.7.</note> 
               <hi>Philemon,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:17891:14"/> and others, not enriched and enabled, how ſhall <hi>Paul,</hi> or the bowels of the Saints be refreſhed? <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> poore afflicted, had friends of ability through the Lord to vphold his ſoule<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal 54 4.</note>, for the Lord (he ſaid) was with them.<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 35.27.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord loueth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity of his ſeruants.</hi> Therefore bleſſed with it, they bleſſe him for it, and<note n="z" place="margin">Iob 31.22.</note> the loynes bleſſe them of all that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed by them, their <hi>righteouſneſſe endureth for euer, and their borne ſhall be exalted with honour</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 112. <hi>vlt.</hi>
               </note>. Neuertheleſſe afflicted
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17891:14"/> without controuerſie,
<list>
                  <item>Outwardly.</item>
                  <item>Inwardly.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Outwardly: reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and enuied for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and doing the thing that good is.<note n="a" place="margin">Eccle. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>I conſidered</hi> (ſaith the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher) <hi>all trauell, and euery right worke, and for this a man is enuied of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Cain,</hi> who was of the wicked one, ſlew <hi>Abel;</hi> wherefore? becauſe his workes were euill, and his brothers righteous<note n="b" place="margin">1 Io. 3.12</note>. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was afflicted of his brethren<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 37.4.</note>, <hi>Daniel</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of the Preſidents<note n="d" place="margin">Dan. 6.4.</note>, Ieſus Chriſt reiected of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17891:15"/> his owne,<note n="e" place="margin">Io. 1.11.</note> and they that exerciſe themſelues to liue godly in him,<note n="f" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.12.</note> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted of vnreaſonable and wicked men<note n="*" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.2.</note>; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? know ye not that there is enmity put be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the ſeed of the woman, and the ſeed of the ſerpent<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note>? <hi>Demetrius</hi> had a good report of all men,<note n="h" place="margin">Io ep. 3. 10, 12.</note> yet <hi>Diotrephes</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt him with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious words; the rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous ſpeake euill of the frugall and moderate, that will not runne with them into the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of riot.<note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet 4.4</note> Thus may the ſeruants of the moſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17891:15"/> high God, liuing other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in as great peace and proſperity as the Carme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite,<note place="margin">Nabal.</note> bee enuied of euill men,<note place="margin">Ier. 18.18.</note> and afflicted with the ſcourge of the tongue, yea,<note place="margin">Iob cap. 1.</note> and ſuffer ſome loſſe in ſome other things, but the LORD, (as the ſeer to <hi>Amaziah</hi>) is able to giue them much more than that,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 25.9.</note> and to make all grace to abound towards them, that they alwayes hauing ſufficiency in all things, (maugre the malicious that enuie and reproach them) may abound vnto euery good worke.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.8.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17891:16"/>2. Inwardly they are afflicted alſo, but how who knoweth? What feare and trembling <hi>in interiori domo,</hi> yea, what carefulneſſe,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 7.11</note> yea, what clearing of themſelues from the aſperſions of the euill, yea, what indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Io. 17.5.</note> yea, what vehement deſire, yea, what zeale, yea, what reuenge vpon themſelues, ouertaken with a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ult vnknowne to the world? This ſo to be who will deny? Not one. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſides, if not in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for themſelues, yet afflicted they are or may be.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17891:16"/>
            <p>In the afflictions
<list>
                  <item>of the Church.</item>
                  <item>of the brethren.</item>
                  <item>of the Lord.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Church.<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 137.1.</note> Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of waters ranne by the riuers of <hi>Babylon, Sion</hi> remembred,<note n="l" place="margin">Neh. 1.3, 4.</note> the ſonne of <hi>Hachaliah,</hi> the people of God his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen in great affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and reproach, the wall of Ieruſalem broken downe, and the gates burnt with fire, ſate down and wept, and mourned certaine daies, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and prayed.<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Vri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> the arke, and Iſrael and <hi>Iudah</hi> in their tents, will not goe downe to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17891:17"/> eat and drinke, and to ſleepe with his wife. The Lord ſaith himſelfe, that in all the afflictions of his people he was afflicted himſelfe.<note n="n" place="margin">Eſai. 63.9</note> The ſpirit of God vpon him, can any man ſay leſſe of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the Churches? In the afflictions of the Chuches in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> who is not affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that is of the Church of the liuing God, the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and ground of truth?<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Of priuate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, eſpecially the holy brethren<note n="*" place="margin">Hob. 3.1.</note>. Other ſicke, and though hard friends, yet <hi>Dauid</hi> would
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17891:17"/> put on ſackcloth, and bee afflicted for them.<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 35.13. 2 Sam. 3.32, 33. 2 Sam. 1.26</note> For <hi>Abner</hi> how much? and for <hi>Ionathan</hi> as <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> for him. <hi>Lazarus</hi> dead, <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid to his fellowes, Let vs goe that wee may die with him<note n="p" place="margin">Io. 11.16.</note>. <hi>Epaphroditus</hi> full of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uineſſe for the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 2.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> becauſe they heard that he had bin ſicke, they hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie for his ſickneſſe, and he for their heauineſſe, <hi>full of heauineſſe,</hi> feeling members ſhould it not be ſo? <hi>The members haue the ſame care one for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.25, 26.</note>, <hi>and if one member ſuffer, all the members ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:17891:18"/> with it;</hi> members we one of another, one body in Chriſt, no ſympathy being in a man, how is he in the body? the rule is,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Heb. 13.3</note> 
               <hi>Remember them that are in bonds as bound with them, and them which ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer aduerſity; as being your ſelues alſo in the body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Of the Lord. Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers he not when the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked riſe vp againſt him<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 139.21</note>, make v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id his law<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 119.126</note>, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke the eyes of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, put downe his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and him to open ſhame<note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 6.6.</note>? When they preſſe him, and hee is preſſed vnder them, as a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17891:18"/> cart with ſheaues<note n="y" place="margin">Amos 2.13.</note> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers he not? or ſuffers he and not his ſeruants with him? How did <hi>Eliakim, Shebua</hi> and <hi>Ioab</hi> rent their cloaths at the blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie of <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Iſaiah 36.22.</note>? How did thoſe that were marked at Ieruſalem ſigh, and cry for all the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations that were done in the midſt therof<note n="a" place="margin">Ezek. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>? How was iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> vexed with the filthy conuerſation of the wicked<note n="b" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.7, 8.</note>? that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man dwelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> in ſeeing and hearing vexed his righteous ſoule from day to day with their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17891:19"/> deeds. <hi>He that can heare &amp; ſee the Lord diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored, his name blaſphemed, his Sabbaths prophaned, his Word deſpiſed, his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters mocked &amp; baſely miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, his worſhip polluted, and perfunctorily perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and is not afflicted. The Lord knoweth whoſe he is, and to whom he belongs, that comes not to his helpe, nor beares his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, nor grieues for that which is ſaid to grieue the holy ſpirit of God.</hi> As <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſaid, honoured of all but of <hi>Mordecai.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eſther 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>All this auaileth me nothing, ſo long as I ſee Mordecai the Iew
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17891:19"/> ſitting at the Kings gate,</hi> ſo ſay thoſe whoſe hearts are vnited to the Lord, and that feare his Name; <hi>Although of themſelues by place and authority they are mighty in power, their ſeed eſtabliſhed in their ſight, their off-ſpring before their eyes, their houſes ſafe from feare, their friends as the ſtarres of heauen for emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and multitude, their wiſdome, and wealth, and worlds delight, as Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons;</hi> All theſe auaile vs nothing, ſo long as we ſee our Lord and our God, ſet behinde, not before the ſons of men, forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17891:20"/> not remembred, expoſed to ſhame, &amp; not honoured in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pondered theſe things:</hi> I may (as I was about) conclude vnder afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the whole houſhold of God, and ſet downe this poſition to ſtand faſt for euer without oppoſition. <hi>That the righteous ſeruants of God, his beloued of his houſhold, haue all their times, (in ſeuerall kindes) as Dauid had in his, of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering in this life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 34.19</note> 
               <hi>Many the afflictions or euils of the righteous, the croſſe, on their ſhoulder, the yoke on their necke, and on their backe the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:17891:20"/> rod of the wicked</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Eſay 48, 10.</note>. Iſrael, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is the Iſrael of God, is refined and choſen in the furnace of affliction.</p>
            <p>Demanded <hi>vnde:</hi> From whence afflictions come &amp; from whom the euils, let <hi>Iob</hi> anſwer;<note n="f" place="margin">Iob 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>Not forth of the duſt, nor out of the ground, but from the Lord.</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Amos 3.6</note> 
               <hi>Shall there be euill in the Citie and the Lord hath not done it. The Lord cauſeth griefe</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lam. 3.32.</note>, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loueth them, he ſcourgeth <hi>his beloued, whom he calleth his called</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Iſai. 48.12, 14.</note>, <hi>whom hee loueth he chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 12.6</note>, yea he hath ſaid<note n="l" place="margin">Reuel. 3.19.</note> 
               <hi>As many as I loue I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17891:21"/> and chaſten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Enquired of <hi>Quorſum;</hi> to what end he doth it? By the ſure word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie the anſwer is,</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the profit of his owne.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And his owne glory.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the profit of his owne: his owne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by being,
<list>
                  <item>1. Viuified.</item>
                  <item>2. Sanctified.</item>
                  <item>3. Purged.</item>
                  <item>4. Preuented.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Viuified or quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Dead in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the liuing, or dull of hearing, ſometimes the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17891:21"/> generation of hs chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and remiſſe in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, in their proſperity as the inhabitants of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon</hi> and <hi>Baſhan, they will not heare</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Ier. 22.21.</note>, nor ſeeke as the <hi>rebellious children</hi> the face of the Lord, but <hi>in their affliction</hi> they will heare him gladly, and <hi>ſeeke him early</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Hoſ. 5. vlt</note>; the mountaine made ſtrong, and ſecurity crying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, <hi>I ſhall neuer be moued,</hi> decryeth other cryes, the people whom the Lord <hi>hath formed for himſelfe,</hi> will not in ſuch a caſe <hi>ſhew forth his praiſe. Iacob</hi> would not, nor would
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17891:22"/> 
               <hi>Iſrael call vpon him,</hi> but <hi>was weary of him</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Iſai. 43.21, 22.</note>, yet the Lord gone his way and <hi>returned to his place,</hi> or his face hid; trouble came, and the their cry was heard, <hi>Come and let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.1.</note>. Correſpondent to the Prophets coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell<note n="q" place="margin">Cap. 14.2.</note>; Take with you words, and turne to the Lord, and <hi>render vnto him the</hi> Calues <hi>of your lippes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Sanctified: parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of afflictions by the hand of the Lord; parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers alſo of his holineſſe<note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 12.10.</note>, made holy thereby<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Non quod nos propriè ſanctificent ſed quod ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicula, &amp;c. Caluin. Hoſm.</hi>
               </note>, yet not properly, for <hi>Chriſt is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:17891:22"/> the ſanctification,</hi> but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed to the moritificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the fleſh, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently prepared <hi>(hauing eſcaped the corruption which is in the world through luſt)</hi> as well to be receiued of the Lord, as alſo to receiue the Lord to be ſanctified in their heart<note n="*" place="margin">Iſai. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note>; their feare, their dread, and their ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary: yea, <hi>Conſortes eſſe,</hi> to be conſorts of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not of the ſubſtance, but of the image of God, <hi>after him created in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and true holineſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or of diuine qualities con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17891:23"/> and predicated as the vertues of him, who <hi>calleth out of darkneſſe into maruellous light</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pet. 2.9.</note>: the ſimile is obuious<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Perkinſ. aur. armil.</hi>
               </note>; As the needle to the threed, ſo the Croſſe makes way to ſanctity, or amendment of life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Purged; Reſty, the Saints grow ruſty, turne againe vnto folly, gather blackneſſe and <hi>filthineſſe both of the fleſh and ſpirit:</hi> fooliſh l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t alone, as <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im to his Idols</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.17</note>, ioyned to the froward, froward, as they; to the ignorant, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, as they; to the brutiſh, brutiſh, as they;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17891:23"/> yea, as beaſts before God<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 73.22.</note>. Behold the man on the mountaine in <hi>the wilderneſſe of Maon, as a dead dogge</hi> in the ſight of the aduerſary that ſought his life<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.14.</note>, but vpon the <hi>roofe of the Kings houſe</hi> as a pampred horſe looking and neighing <hi>after his neighbours wife</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 11.2. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 5 8.</note> not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out from veſſell to veſſel; <hi>Moah</hi> like, men ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle on their lees: Peace abuſed, defileth, and reſt corrupteth thoſe who by reaſon of their reſt haue not their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcerne good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill. Is the prophecie
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:17891:24"/> hard in <hi>Dan</hi> 11.35. touching men of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: may wee not heare it? <hi>ſurely ſuch men fall ſometimes,</hi> yet ſuffer no loſſe<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vt radicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, hoc eſt herba lana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, qua a fullonibus haec and is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betur, pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert ad mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiem &amp; canderem lana ſeu panni: ita perſecutio atque affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctio ſubigit ecoleſiam, &amp;c. Polan. in Dan.</hi> 11.32.</note>, but are as ſoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led wooll with ſopeweed, or fouled cloth with Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers earth, purged by meanes of the later blot from a former ſpot, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret fault before not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. Who can vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the error of his way without a fall, or will waſh or purge no filth of the fleſh ſeene to put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, nor felt ill humors in the body to expurge. Remember the Patriarks,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17891:24"/> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.22. and 50.15.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Preuented or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from two great euills, which other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or left to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, precipitate or headlong caſt themſelues into: namely, tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and condemnation. Obſtacles to theſe, the thornes of afflictions, in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 2.6. <hi>I will hedge vp thy way with thornes,</hi> ſaith the Lord, to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Zanch. in loc. Non poſſe intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi niſi de electis, &amp;c. Sapè enim etiam electi inducunt in anima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> not of the children of whoredomes, but of the Elect; for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the Elect, either of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, or of infirmity, or according to the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:17891:25"/> of carnall wiſdome, and motions of the fleſh, determine with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to follow often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>after ſtrange louers, lying vanities, forbidden pleaſures, things vnſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and inconuenient,</hi> or not acceptable vnto the Lord, therefore the Lord walls vp their wayes, ſets bryars in their pathes, ſends croſſes, ſo thicke, that (as <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1. Sam. 23.27, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8</note> from purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Dauid</hi> by the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines</hi> inuading the land,) they<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are turned from their intended euill cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: <hi>into the way vnto ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie:</hi> Their firſt huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17891:25"/> 
               <hi>i.</hi> the Lord their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker found to be the beſt<note n="d" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.7.</note>, conſequently kept backe from the great tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 19.13.</note>, likewiſe from condemnation; for <hi>when they are iudged, they are chaſtened of the Lord, that they ſhould not be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the world</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.32.</note>. The whole world lieth in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe<note n="g" place="margin">1 Ioh. 5.19.</note>, but they that are of God are called, and called out, and common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come out thorow the fornace of Affliction<note n="h" place="margin">Iſai. 48.10.</note>, <hi>Eſay</hi> 48.10.</p>
            <p>Thus for their owne profit: followeth for the glorie of the Lord,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:17891:26"/> The Lord glorified, In his
<list>
                  <item>Power,</item>
                  <item>and Prouidence.</item>
               </list> By their
<list>
                  <item>Faith,</item>
                  <item>and Obedience.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In his power: His <hi>power made perfect in their weakneſſe</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 12.9.</note>, weake they, <hi>they are ſtrong in him;</hi> or falling through infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>he vpholdeth them with his hand</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 37.17, 24.</note>: In his hand they are, and <hi>no man ſhall pluck them out of his hand</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. 10.28, 29.</note>. The mightie man may boaſt himſelfe in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe; but the power of the Lord, as his goodnes,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:17891:26"/> endureth continually<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 52.1.</note>; thornes may <hi>be in the fleſh</hi> of the faithfull, the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Satan buffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them; but the grace of the Lord, which is with them, is proued ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for them<note n="n" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.9.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his prouidence: drawne vnto him <hi>with the cords of a man and bands of loue,</hi> he <hi>taketh by the armes</hi> his deare children<note n="o" place="margin">Hoſ. 11.3, 4.</note> and <hi>teacheth them to goe;</hi> fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them, clotheth them, ſtirreth vp others to ſuſtaine their ſoules: As Rauens miniſtred to <hi>Eliah,</hi> ſo ſupplyes are ſent by them, whom hee will
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17891:27"/> ſend. In the dayes of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine they eat, and haue enough<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 37.19.</note>; for as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah</hi> and his people, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem beleaguered<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 37.30</note>, they either eat <hi>ſuch as groweth of it ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>that which ſpringeth of the ſame:</hi> Or elſe, as the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues of Iudah<note n="r" place="margin">Dan. 1.15.</note> fed with pulſe, their countenance appeareth fairer and fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than other, which eat the portion of the Kings meat. Sometimes by ſmall meanes, ſometimes by no meanes, ſometimes againſt meanes, (in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining and preſeruing them<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet 5.7.</note> that caſt their care
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:17891:27"/> on him) he beyond expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, or mans appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, declareth his care of them, and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrateth his prouidence ſo luculently, that all cry out, as the Magitians in Aegypt; <hi>This is the finger of God</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Exod. 8.19.</note>, <hi>Exod.</hi> 8.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By their faith: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and found <hi>vnto praiſe and honour</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Deut. 8.2.</note>, knowen in the tentation <hi>what is in the heart, viz.</hi> vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and readineſſe to draw neere vnto God<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 73. vlt.</note>, and to <hi>cleaue vnto the Lord with full purpoſe of heart</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſa. 42.8.</note>, <hi>prayer made to the God of their life, &amp;c. Chriſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17891:28"/> followed, the croſſe taken vp, themſelues denied,</hi> yea<note n="y" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>preſſed out of meaſure and aboue ſtrength, the ſentence of death receiued in themſelues, that they might not truſt in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues but in God, which after</hi> two dayes<note n="z" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.2.</note> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he kill) <hi>raiſeth the dead:</hi> magnified and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in their bodie their Lord and their God; whether by life, as in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 18.17, 18.</note>; or by death, as in <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ioh. 21.19.</note>. <hi>In the end of their faith</hi> is the end of the Lord; his owne glorie in their ſaluation<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 50.23.</note> corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and ſpirituall, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17891:28"/> and eternall, according to his word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15.<note n="*" place="margin">Saepè hic &amp; innocin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes pereunt, &amp; recti ſunditùs delentur, ſed tamen ad aeternam glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iam pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rcundo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantur. Greg. lib. <hi>5.</hi> Mor. cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note>.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By their obedience: honoured as a father of his ſonnes<note n="d" place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>ſubmiſſe in their affliction;</hi> and a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of his ſeruants, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected <hi>obſequious, and not anſwering againe</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Tit. 2.9.</note>. Had not Satan conſidered <hi>Iob</hi> the ſeruant of God<note n="f" place="margin">Iob. 1.8.</note> in his proſperitie? Enough he did to his owne ſhame and the glorie of the Lord in his aduerſitie: for as Ieſus Chriſt (though he were a ſonne) <hi>learned obedience by the things which he ſuffered</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 5.9.</note>:
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:17891:29"/> ſo <hi>Iob,</hi> and all the ſonnes of God <hi>by faith in Chriſt Ieſus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 3.26.</note>, learne of him <hi>to be lowly in heart</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Matt. 11.29.</note>, and by the things which they ſuffer obedience to their <hi>father, which is in heaven. Better</hi> this <hi>than ſacrifice,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> Bullocks <hi>with hornes and hoofes not required,</hi> but obedience from <hi>the heart to the forme of doctrine which is deliuered</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 5.17.</note>: ſtrange fleſh not to be offered; but a mans owne fleſh to bee ſacrificed, which in euerie act of obedience is done;<note n="*" place="margin">Per vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctimas alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na caro per obedientiam jam verò propria caro mactatur, &amp;c. Gr. ſup. <hi>1</hi> Reg. c. <hi>15.</hi> Obedire eſt contra audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, ſcilicet contra pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priam vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem. Vt. Perald. Sum. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> par. <hi>10.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> in fin.</note> 
               <hi>crucified the fleſh,</hi> which luſteth <hi>againſt the Spirit</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 6.17.</note>, in which it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:17891:29"/> obeyed the word, which <hi>commeth,</hi> and the Lord therein <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding proſperouſly</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 45.4.</note>. This cauſeth honour to God in his Maieſtie; yea ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, yet without to glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him in the day of viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation<note n="o" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.12.</note>.</p>
            <p>The cauſes of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons efficient and finall thus diſcouered, I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the Vſes which ſhall be For
<list>
                  <item>1. Reproofe.</item>
                  <item>2. Correction.</item>
                  <item>3. Information.</item>
                  <item>4. Admonition.</item>
                  <item>5. Inſtruction.</item>
                  <item>6. Inſtauration.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:17891:30"/> Vnto which ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a word of Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For reproofe to the vile <hi>Barbarians,</hi> which ſeeing a viper on a <hi>Pauls</hi> hand, or a croſſe laid on a <hi>Simons</hi> ſhoulder, cry out they arc murtherers or malefactors, and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance will not ſuffer them to liue at eaſe, or to proſper as other men; but theſe the brutiſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people; fooles alas, when will ye vnderſtand<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 94.8</note>? <hi>The time is come, that iudgement muſt begin at the houſe of God,</hi> and if it firſt begin with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:17891:30"/> them that profeſſe and obey, <hi>what ſhall the end be of them that obey not,</hi> nor profeſſe <hi>the Goſpell of God?</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaued, where ſhall the vngodly and the ſinner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare?</hi> If this be done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the green trees, which bring forth fruit accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as God hath dealt the <hi>meaſure of the ſpirit,</hi> what ſhall bee done vnto the dry, which digd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and dreſſed yeare after yeare, continue yet fruitleſſe, as the curſed fig-tree? If the way vnto Heaven bee ſtrewed with croſſes, bee full of tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17891:31"/> and tribulations, what ſhall be found in the way vnto hell, or in the end thereof?<note n="r" place="margin">Pro. 14.12.</note> 
               <hi>There is a way which ſeemeth right vnto a man,</hi> as the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l of the Gentiles vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues,<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>laſciuiouſneſſe, luſts, exceſſe of wine, reuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, banquettings, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable idolatries, but the end thereof are the wayes of death.</hi> Remember ye not the words of the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, how he ſaid,<note place="margin">Luk. 6.25.</note> Woe vnto you that now laugh, for ye ſhall weepe? weep when the righteous, at whoſe troubles they laugh, ſhall be deliuered
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17891:31"/> out of all, and they come in their ſtead. Doe yee thinke that the Scripture ſaith in vaine; The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is deliuered out of trouble, and the wicked commeth in his ſtead<note n="u" place="margin">Pro. 11.8.</note>? Againe, The wicked ſhall bee a ranſome for the righteous,<note n="x" place="margin">Pro. 21.18. Dan. 6.24.</note> and the tranſgreſſor for the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right? Inſtances, before experience had, the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles had of God. <hi>Haman</hi> and <hi>Mordecai</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Eſth. 7.10</note> 
               <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and the Aethiopians<note n="z" place="margin">Iſai. 43.3.</note>, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> and his accuſers, <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and his keepers.<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 12.19.</note> But <hi>Barbarians</hi> are <hi>blinde,</hi> and <hi>cannot ſee afarre off:</hi> The
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:17891:32"/> 
               <hi>iudgements of God are far aboue, out of their ſight</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 10.5.</note>, on other ſeene, not ouer themſelues; themſelues in the <hi>condemnation,</hi> vnto which before they were ordained of old, they finde not, not made to ſuffer euill with the Saints in the earth, but for the euill day<note n="b" place="margin">Pro. 16.4.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> 2. For correction to them that refuſe corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction:<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 1.3, 4.</note> Such was the <hi>ſinfull nation, the people la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with iniquitie, the ſeed of euill doers, the children that were corrupters.</hi> That had forſaken the Lord, and prouoked the holy
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17891:32"/> one of Iſrael vnto anger, not only by going away backward, but by refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to returne. <hi>The one knoweth his owner,</hi> and what the pricke of the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad meaneth, but Iſrael did not know, neither did they conſider: therefore the Prophet to them<note n="d" place="margin">Ver. 5.</note>, <hi>Why ſhould yee bee ſtricken any more, yee will reuolt more and more. Ieremiah</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 5.3.</note> hath the like complaint, <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſmitten them, but they haue not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, thou haſt conſumed them, but they haue refuſed to receiue correction: they haue made them faces har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:17891:33"/> than a rocke, they haue refuſed to returne.</hi> It is ſo with many: Many there bee that being afflicted, know it not: As <hi>Ephraim</hi> had <hi>gray haires here and there vpon him, yet knew it not,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Hoſ. 7.9.</note> nor that his <hi>ſtrength was deuoured of ſtrangers:</hi> ſo wrath is on ſome from before the Lord, yet they feele it not, or if they feele it, they are humbled no more than the King of Iſrael by the famine in Samaria. Behold, hee cryed<note n="g" place="margin">2 Reg. 6.33.</note>, <hi>This euill of the Lord, wherefore ſhould I wait on the Lord any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</hi> What hope is in, or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:17891:33"/> is of ſuch? Not the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor which is firme, but the Spiders web which periſheth: <hi>Woe vnto the people that be in ſuch a caſe;</hi> what is ours now? The Church in <hi>tribulation: S. Iohn</hi> ſubſcribed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc.</hi> 1.9. <hi>A brother and Companion in tribulation.</hi> How doe wee? or what? when? When <hi>Hannibal</hi> beſieged S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>guntum, a confederate Citie with Rome; the Capitoll of Rome, one ſaid, was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailed: the danger and loſſe abroad is ours, ours the common calamities
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:17891:34"/> of the dayes; the dayes are euill, yea, ſo euill they are, that a man may ſay, <hi>I haue no pleaſure in them</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 60.1, 2, 3.</note>. <hi>Hath not the Lord caſt vs off? Hath hee not ſcattered vs? Is hee not diſpleaſed with v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>? Doth not the earth tremble? Is it not broken? Doth it not ſhake? Haue wee not hard things ſhewed vs, and beene made to drinke the wine of aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment?</hi> Behold we not the ſhaking of the hand of the Lord, which hee ſhaketh ouer vs? ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched our ſtill, not turned away his wrath<note n="i" place="margin">Iſa. 9.12.17.21.</note>, for all that is done: the enemie
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:17891:34"/> hath <hi>done exploits, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth horribly, boaſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in miſchiefe,</hi> cryeth <hi>there, there, ſo would wee haue it,</hi> enſignes <hi>ſet up for ſignes, the profeſsion in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Religion in the ſtraits, ſchiſme and vngratious he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie a float, a floud of many waters roares in our eares, the firſt borne of many,</hi> the hope of Germany how ſuddenly ſurrepted? Ah alas, The Lord calleth vs to <hi>weeping, and to mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to baldneſſe, and to girding with ſachcloth</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iſa. 22.12, 13.</note>, yet behold among vs <hi>ioy and gladneſſe, ſlaying oxen, killing ſheepe, eating fleſh,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:17891:35"/> and drinking wine;</hi> diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and reſolute we, we refuſe to be reformed, we walke <hi>contrarie to the Lord,</hi> who ſtriketh, and walketh therefore <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto vs,</hi> yea <hi>in furie,</hi> as hee ſpake in <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26.<note n="l" place="margin">Leuit. 26.28.</note>. chaſtizing and puniſhing vs <hi>ſeuen times more,</hi> rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious more and more. I cloſe with one of <hi>Ieremies</hi> Lamentations,<note n="m" place="margin">Ier. 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>When I would comfort my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſorrow, my heart is faint in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> 3. For information; and ſith that the Lord af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicteth whom he loueth, may the afflicted bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:17891:35"/> by three notes, whether or no they are afflicted in loue. For firſt, whom the Lord lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, hee loueth vnto the end, and will not ceaſe from arguing and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening them vntill they be conuerted and reclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſo much the ſpirit expreſly<note n="n" place="margin">Reuel. 3.19.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: As fathers conuince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they chaſtiſe their children, make knowne their faults and multiply ſtripes, vntill they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; promiſe reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: ſemblably the Lord; not leaue will hee them, whom he chuſeth, halting
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17891:36"/> betweene two; but cauſe them by chaſtening them to approach vnto him<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 65.4. and 94.12. compared.</note>. The purifying hand vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, the droſſe is purely purged, and the tinne taken away<note n="p" place="margin">Iſa. 1.25.</note>: eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſonne which is ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, commeth out from among the <hi>multitude which doe euill,</hi> toucheth not <hi>the vncleane thing</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.17.</note>, is thorowly ſeparated, before hee bee receiued, or can be. Bee it ſo, that the wicked <hi>(the hooke in their noſe)</hi> returne not, are not purged in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace from their filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor will bee;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17891:36"/> what ſhall bee done? <hi>Not purged thereby, they ſhall neuer hee purged</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Ezek. 24.13.</note>. <hi>Veſſels of wrath</hi> to be filled with the furie of the Lord: But correction in loue cauſeth the <hi>Beloued</hi> to come in, <hi>confeſsing their ſins,</hi> and their <hi>profiting</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in the <hi>amendment of their life. Dauid</hi> ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, was ſenſible of his fault, and corrigible; the correction of the Lord he refuſed not, but recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for his good, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the ſame; <hi>Good it is for me, that I haue beene af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, that I may learne thy ſtatutes</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 119.67.71.</note>, for before I
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17891:37"/> was <hi>afflicted I went aſtray,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.67.71.</note> 
               <hi>but now haue I kept thy word. Manaſſeh</hi> taken among the thornes, and bound with ſetters, knew at length that <hi>the Lord he was God</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">2 Chron. 33.12.</note>. <hi>Ephraim</hi> bowed, yeelded<note n="u" place="margin">Ier. 31.20.</note>. <hi>Iſrael vexed with all aduerſitie, torne and ſmitten,</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched<note n="x" place="margin">Hoſ 6.1, 2.</note>. When a man chaſtized approacheth vnto the Lord, and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe, confeſſeth and forſaketh his ſin, hee may count it all ioy; yea, giue <hi>glorie to the Lord,</hi> and make thus confeſſion.<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 119.76.</note> 
               <hi>I know, O Lord, that thy iudgments are right, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:17891:37"/> that thou haſt in faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe afflicted thy ſeruant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>2</label> The ſecond loue-token is <hi>Conſolation,</hi> receiued in <hi>the dayes of euill,</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated afterwards: for whom the Lord loueth, he comforteth <hi>in euerie tribulation,</hi> and inableth them thereby to <hi>comfort them which are in any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</hi> By the comforts wherewith they were themſelues comforted of God.<note n="z" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.4, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>As ſufferings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, ſo conſolation aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,</hi> and is participated to them that are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſufferings. <hi>Dauid</hi> ſcourged for his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:17891:38"/> ſin was comforted, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for it; afterwards what would hee? <hi>Teach tranſgreſſours the wayes of God, &amp; conuert ſinners vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 51.13.</note>. <hi>Peter</hi> hauing erred, and being conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, what ſhould hee? <hi>ſtrengthen his brethren</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 22.32.</note>. When a man is refreſhed being afflicted, and as he hath <hi>receiued any grace,</hi> if he <hi>as a good ſteward mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the ſame</hi> vnto other lying in the like diſtreſſe, and <hi>communicate with their affliction,</hi> he hath not been afflicted and refreſhed in vaine: but to good effect, in <hi>loue and in mercie,</hi> to be
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:17891:38"/> a veſſell of mercie, and conduit of loue, from the fountaine to the ciſterne, from the <hi>Lord</hi> to his <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen in the great tribulation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>3</label> The third is a minde content with the <hi>preſent things,</hi> and <hi>preſent ſtate:</hi> this the <hi>obſignation of the ſpirit</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.30.</note>, a certaine diuine impreſſion of light, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret manifeſtation of grace, the <hi>God of all grace</hi> to them that open vnto him, when hee knocketh at their doore, with the hammer of the croſſe, <hi>manifeſting</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Io. 14.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>himſelfe</hi> in an admirable manner; and filling their hearts
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:17891:39"/> with vnexpreſſible glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note n="e" place="margin">Act. 14.17</note>, <hi>giuing them Manna, ſupping with them</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Reu. 3.20.</note>, <hi>brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them to the banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting houſe</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Cant. 2.4, 5.</note>, <hi>ſtaying them with flagons, comforting them with apples, girding their hearts with his peace, which paſſeth vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 4 7.</note>, <hi>powring the ſpirit of grace and ſupplications vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Zach. 12.10.</note>, <hi>giuing them an vnderſtanding, that they may know him that is true</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">1 Io 5.20.</note>, opening the treaſures of his all-ſufficiencie, faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning their hearts, and adapting their mindes to the preſent condition, whatſoeuer it is: no ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:17891:39"/> nor agreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe between the minde and the condition. What is the life but a kinde of liuing death? but ſuiting and agreeing the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the minde, the appetite accommodated, and thing deſired had; had is <hi>that one thing,</hi> which is <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> as it were all things. Men of heauie hearts, mirth and muſike grieue, when as weeping and complaints may bee pleaſant: company offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue, priuacie may pleaſe, and pouertie be an eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, abundance being a burthen. <hi>Euerie bitter
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:17891:40"/> thing is ſweet,</hi> trouble as peace, ſickneſſe as health, impriſonment as libertie, reproach as good report, paine as pleaſure, death as life. If the heart bee ſutable, and the ſpirit made pliable to the mold into which the Lord hath caſt a man; the inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deſires, cauſes, of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtitude, nothing elſe: <hi>The liues not falling in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant places,</hi> nor the <hi>heritage ſo goodly as other mens: a liuing man complaineth,</hi> but euerie one that is godly <hi>is dumbe.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 39.9.</note> 
               <hi>openeth not his mouth, knoweth how to bee abaſed,</hi> and <hi>how to abound,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:17891:40"/> is <hi>euerie where, and in all</hi> things <hi>inſtructed,</hi> both <hi>to be full, and to be hungrie,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Phil. 4.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>both to abound and to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer need, made perfect, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, ſtrengthened, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pet. 5.10.</note> taught of God, and hath learned in <hi>whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſtate hee is, therewith to bee content;</hi> the croſſe his crowne, the ſhame thereof his glorie, his loſſe his aduantage, his yoke his eaſe, or not bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denous and grieuous, but eaſie and light: All his euills good in effect, and <hi>working all together for his good</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 8.28.</note>, from whence is patience? from whence
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:17891:41"/> experience? from whence hope? Verily from <hi>tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> and theſe three a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding, no man is aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the day of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>becauſe the loue of God is ſhed abroad in his heart</hi> by the Comforter, <hi>the Holy Ghoſt which is giuen vnto him</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 5.5.</note>: a loue-ticke the affliction, and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with contentment the proofe thereof.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> 4. For Admonition vnto all, and that all may gather ſome; I will ſuffer it to fall, and to breake off it ſelfe into theſe foure peeces.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. That none worke
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:17891:41"/> out their croſſes, as the ſpider her web, out of their owne bowels, by ryot, of vnrighteouſnes, irregular walking, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate liuing. <hi>Let none of you ſuffer as an euill doer, or a buſie bodie</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.13.</note>. This not thank worthy, that which is acceptable is the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, which is for well-doing, or otherwiſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God, and the good pleaſure of his will: <hi>Therefore take he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d; know and conſider what yee doe; that yee your ſelues doe not vndoe your ſelues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That none willingly cauſe other mens griefes;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:17891:42"/> or be hard-hearted to the poore afflicted <hi>in the power of their hand.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Magna abominatio eor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m Deo eſt, afflicto addere affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionem; clamat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in coelum vox ſanguinis. Oecolampad. in Eſa. <hi>47.6.</hi>
               </note> In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. from the ſixth to the ſixteenth verſe, is a fearfull curſe denounced againſt a <hi>ſonne of perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the cauſe expreſſed; becauſe <hi>he remembred not to ſhew mercie, but perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the poore and needie man, that he might euen ſlay the broken in heart:</hi> The Lord <hi>will be iealous</hi> for his afflicted, with <hi>a great iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie,</hi> yea, verie ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with <hi>them that are at eaſe, and helpe forward the affliction</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Zech. 1.13, 14.</note>. The daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:17891:42"/> 
               <hi>Ladie of Kingdomes</hi> that <hi>was giuen to pleaſure, dwelt careleſly: truſted in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> ſhewed no mercie to the children of the captiuitie, laid not the wrath to heart, neither remembred the latter end, periſhed in her latter end<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 47.6, 7 8 9, 10, 11.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore take yee heed how yee oppreſſe,</hi> or grieue other men, leſt <hi>bitterneſſe</hi> bee euen <hi>your owne hurt and hearts griefe in the end thereof.</hi> It diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſeth the Lord<note n="m" place="margin">Pro. 24.17.</note>, if a man reioyce when <hi>his enemie falleth;</hi> or <hi>ſuffer his heart to be glad when he ſtumbleth;</hi> much more if
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:17891:43"/> he ſmite with <hi>the fiſt of wickedneſſe</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 58.4.</note>, and put a ſtumbling blocke before the innocent, or afflict ſuch as be of vpright con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 37.14.</note>; yea, it is a <hi>righteous thing with God, to recompence tribulation to them</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">2 Theoſſ. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>that trouble them, which would lead a quiet and peaceable life in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and honeſtie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. That we ſlight not the ſurpriſall of other men, but conſider our ſelues, that we our ſelues in an houre yet vnknown, may be alſo ouertaken<note n="q" place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note>, <hi>Ille hod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>è,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; ego cras;</hi> He to day, and I to morrow,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:17891:43"/> a Fathers feare, and may bee ours: our looking-glaſſe euerie mans euill, wherein wee may ſee our owne, preſent, or elſe to come. The breaches of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> not remembred, made breaches on them that remembred them not: Gallant-like they liued in pleaſure, and were wanton on the earth, and nouriſhed their hearts, as in a day of ſlaughter, but were not grieued for the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Amos 6.6, 7.</note>, vntill they went captiue with the firſt that went captiue, &amp; their banquet was remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:17891:44"/>
            <p>Therefore take ye heed, and remember the ſaying familiar as the Engliſh rules, <hi>Felix quem faciunt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Happie is the man whom other mens harmes doe make to beware.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. That we ſecure not our ſelues, ſaying, Peace and ſafetie, becauſe of the preſent peace; and ſoule take thine eaſe, becauſe of the preſent ſafetie<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Theſ. 5.3.</hi> Neſcimus quid ſerus veſper ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat.</note>, for who knoweth what a day may bring forth<note n="t" place="margin">1 Pro. 24.1.</note>, the deſtruction may bee ſudden, and if a blow bee giuen on the blinde ſide, wee ſhall not know well bow to take it well, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:17891:44"/> are fore-ſhewed, ſhould bee therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; for as <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Act. 20.23.</note> for the Holy Ghoſt witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that afflictions abide all them that are Chriſts, and perſecutions to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer; the externall peace continued, is for the men of this preſent euill world, which haue their portion in this life<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 17.14.</note> whoſe backes are freed from the rod of God<note n="y" place="margin">Iob 21.</note>, and bellies filled with hid treaſures, their houſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe from feare, and poſſeſſions paſſing the thoughts of their heart<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 73 7.</note>, ſet yet in ſlipperie places,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:17891:45"/> and brought into deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in a moment<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 73.19.</note>; they ſpend their dayes in mirth and wealth, but in a moment goe downe to the grau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iob 21.13.</note>. A kinde of pond they haue, or a land-floud which abideth not, the well-ſprings of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> mourne being affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted; Better this ſo to bee affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and to mourne, than gaining the world to loſe the ſoule, or enjoying the pleaſures of ſin for a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be caſt out bound into vtter darkneſſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore in this our day let vs hearken vnto
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:17891:45"/> wiſdome, crying with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and as <hi>Aſah</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">2 Chron. 14.6, 7.</note> built fenced cities in <hi>Iudah,</hi> when the land had reſt; lets edifie our ſelues on our moſt holy faith<note n="b" place="margin">Iude v. 20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our Creator<note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.2.1.</note>, and worke out our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<note n="d" place="margin">Phil. 2.12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>, that when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption determined<note n="e" place="margin">Iſai <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.22.</note> ſhall come, or the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing ſcourge<note n="f" place="margin">Ver. 15.</note>, or the houre of temptation vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the world<note n="g" place="margin">Reuel. 3.10.</note>, wee may, as the iuſt<note n="h" place="margin">Hab. 2.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> liue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y faith, dwell ſafely, and bee quiet from feare of euill, according to the word<note n="i" place="margin">Pro. 1.33.</note>.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> 5. For inſtruction vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:17891:46"/> the afflicted, to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed as the former; diuided the whole into fiue parts, that the ſame may <hi>partitè,</hi> peecemeale as it were, and ſo the more eaſily, be taken and laid vp.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber their miſery, the worm wood and the gall, that their ſoules haue the ſame ſtill in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and be humbled thereby, for therein is the hope<note n="k" place="margin">Iam. 3.20, 21.</note>.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring according to the will of God, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their way, and the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:17891:46"/> keeping of their ſoules in well doing vnto God, as to a faithfull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,<note n="l" place="margin">1. Pet. 4, vlt.</note> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. <hi>vlt.</hi> Able he is to keepe that which is committed vnto him. Faithfull he is, and will not ſuffer the faithfull to bee tempted aboue that they are able, but will with the temptation alſo make a way to eſcape, that they may be able to beare it<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cor. 10.13.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that they pray: Let a man afflicted pray<note n="n" place="margin">Iam. 5.13.</note>, pray continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally<note n="o" place="margin">Col 4.5.</note>, continue in prayer, and watch in the ſame with thankſgiuing, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:17891:47"/> thanks for the grace preſent, by which Satan is reſiſted, and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then ſuſtained, praying alſo with all prayer and ſupplication in the ſpirit, that the burthen on them may bee taken of them, prayer the meanes to remoue it; for he who heareth prayer hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen his word, that inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated in the time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he will deliuer them that call vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n his name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.15.<note n="*" place="margin">Ideo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuntur iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, vt cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aud antur, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uditi glorificent Deum. Aug. in loc.</note>
            </p>
            <p>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urthly, that by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ience they poſſeſſe their ſoules<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 21.19.</note>, and as the <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalonians</hi> cauſe other to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:17891:47"/> glory for their patience and faith in all their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions and tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note n="q" place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.4.</note>. This the <hi>victorie of the Saints</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Reu. 13.10.14.12.</note>, the iſſue of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 5.3.</note>, the effect of the word<note n="t" place="margin">Reu. 3.10.</note>; this the dawning of light, on the ſprenting of that ſeed which is ſowen for the righteous. In <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.11. Light, <hi>i.</hi> peace and proſperity, the fruit of righteouſneſſe, is ſowen for the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>in the dayes of euill ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in darknes</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Micah. 7.8.</note>. A phraſe from the plough; Good ſeed ſowen in fallowes broken vp, lieth for a time couered in, the ground,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:17891:48"/> and ſprouteth not ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, but in its ſeaſon: In their ſufferings it is ſo with the ſeruants of God; Their hearts furrowed with the culter of the Croſſe, the word of pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence caſt vpon it by the hand of faith, the harrow of godly ſorrow drawen ouer and ouer it in the conuulſions thereof; In his time the Lord com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, and raineth on them righteouſnes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in vnto themſelues they had ſowed<note n="u" place="margin">Hoſ. 10.12.</note>, and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiue peace, the peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fruit of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> is in full ſheaues
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:17891:48"/> brought in a time accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted home into their barnes; their barnes are filled, yea their hearts, with food and gladneſſe, by their hard and tedious labours indured; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore counted happie they that indure: <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>we count them happie that indure</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iam. 5.11.</note> Of the patience of <hi>Iob,</hi> that happie man, no man is ignorant, nor ſo blinde, but may ſee in him the end of the Lord, <hi>that hee is verie pitifull, and of tender mercie.</hi> They that wait on him renew their ſtrength, mount vp with
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:17891:49"/> wings as Eagles, run and are not wearie, walke and are nor faint:<note n="z" place="margin">Eſa. 40.31.</note> for as they on him, ſo waiteth he on them, that he may be gratious vnto them; and will be exalted<note n="a" place="margin">Eſa. 30.18.</note>, that he may haue mercy vpon them. O how bleſſed are all they that wait for him<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 2.12. Pſal. 34.2. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 16.20. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 77.</note>!</p>
            <p>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fthly, that they ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tisfie themſelues as with the likeneſſe of God, when they awake<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 17.15.</note>, ſo with his preſence, while they ſleepe, or walke ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thorow the valley of the ſhadow of death, their eyes withholden
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:17891:49"/> with the preſent preſſures that they cannot ſleepe; <hi>Sufficient to the day is the euill thereof</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 6. vlt.</note> ſufficient to the euill dayes the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>El Schaddai,</hi> God all-ſufficient: who but hee in heauen<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal 73.25.</note>, and in earth beſides him what to be deſired? In him all <hi>liue, and moue, and haue their being</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Act 17.28</note>, <hi>the Author he and finiſher of faith</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Heb. 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>; All and in all that haue faith in him. In Heauen what need ſhall be of the Sun, or of the Moone,<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 60 11.19.</note> or of candle, or of victuall, or of veſture, or of lands, or of liuings? Not any: for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:17891:50"/> the Lord will be All, <hi>All in Heauen, and in earth All things.</hi> Therefore ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring need, what need of any thing more than of God, to ſit in the minde, and to frame the ſame to the preſent ſtate, or to dwell in the heart, and to fill the ſame with food and gladnes? The minde on him, and hee in the minde; the heart on him, and he in the heart, what want of the creatures, or of other gifts? Is not all want ſupplyed with his fulneſſe? What wanted <hi>Moſes? Elocution:</hi> What anſwer from God had he
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:17891:50"/> but this,<note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 4.11, 12.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath made mans mouth?</hi> I will be with thy mouth. Would God be a mouth vnto him, or a tongue in his mouth? In effect he would, and fully be as good, yea better for vſe, and more effectuall; of all other things wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the afflicted, the like may bee ſaid, <hi>Who made them?</hi> Orphans want their parents; who made their parents? He that made their parents will be vnto them in ſtead of parents: Parents want their children; who made their children? He that made their children,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:17891:51"/> will be vnto them in ſtead of children: widdowes want their husbands; who made their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands? Hee that made their husbands, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll bee with them in ſtead of husbands: widdowers want their wiues; who made their wiues? Hee that made their wiues will bee with them in ſtead of wiues: brethren want their ſiſters; who made their ſiſters? Hee that made their ſiſters will be vnto them in ſtead of ſiſters: ſiſters want their brethren; who made their brethren? He that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:17891:51"/> made their brethren will be with them in ſtead of brethren: the poore af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, perſecuted, want their houſes, lands, meanes, liuelihood; who made all, and gaue all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all? He that made all, and gaue them all, will be vnto them inſtead of all Varieties of comforts, in the varietie of the creatures; Parents af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford one k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nde of ſolace, children another, huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands another, wiues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, brethren ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſiſters another, lands and ſuch like meanes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; but the Lord he
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:17891:52"/> 
               <hi>is God of all conſolation, not any without him in any thing, but with him is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in euery thing.</hi> And hee with his affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted, whats the euill on them or againſt them? He with them in exile, whats their exile? He with them in priſon, whats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> impriſonment? he with them in diſgrace, whats their diſgrace? He with them in pouerty, whats their pouerty? He with them in perſecution, whats their perſecution? much aduantage, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way much: What protection from the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:17891:52"/> Lord? what propagati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpell?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> what recompence of reward without perſecution? <hi>With perſecution in this life an hundred ſold ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mar. 10.30.</note>: &amp; in what but in the preſence of the Lord, and the efficacie of his grace, which is equiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, yea an hundred fold more excellent than the loſſe? I know not what better ſenſe can be giuen, or how otherwiſe that reading is to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: Had he ſaid, that after the ceſſation of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, peace ſhall bee and wealth, &amp;c. plaine
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:17891:53"/> it had beene, but he ſaith with perſecution in the time thereof a man ſhall receiue an hundred fold, and that is as plaine to them that haue the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in themſelues. In few to ſhut vp the whole matter: <hi>Marke the man that ſhrinketh vnder the hand of God, and behold him that maketh the Lord his Committee, that prayeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afflicted, that waiteth patiently, carrying the Lords leaſure, and ſatisfied with the preſence of his grace as ſufficient, endureth to the end; for the end of that man is peace</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:17891:53"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> 4. For the inſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them,<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 3 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>That giue willingly their cheekes to him that ſmiteth them, that are filled with bitterneſſe, and made drunken with wormewood, couered with aſhes, and their teeth broken as with grauell ſtones, their ſoule remoued far off from peace, and proſperitie forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Scriptura v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cat bonos f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>umentum, malos pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am, eritur ventus, &amp;c. Fon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſec. Sabb. ante Dom. Quad.</note> For good men the Scripture calleth <hi>wheat,</hi> the euill <hi>chaffe,</hi> ariſeth a great wind of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or commeth from the wilderneſſe ſome <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Blaſt</hi> of other ſore affliction, to diſſociate the good and the euill, to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:17891:54"/> ſegregate the <hi>pretious from the vile,</hi> and as wheat from the chaffe, to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate true Iſraelites, in whom no guile is, from <hi>potſheards couered with ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer droſſe</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizers hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</note>. Are the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens now blacke <hi>with clouds and winds,</hi> doe the winds blow, be the times boyſterous, the dayes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, the world troublous? The Lord is about to <hi>purge his floore,</hi> and will purge it thorowly<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>:<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 3.12.</note> the <hi>wheat</hi> he will gather into his garner, but the <hi>chaffe</hi> hee will <hi>ſcatter;</hi> yea burne it with vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able fire.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:17891:54"/>
            <p>
               <hi>After a fierie triall, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours may be fewer, but ſhall be better farre</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Conjectae eccleſia in catinum, &amp; excocta igne affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionum, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor quidem euadit ſed p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ior. Amand. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan. in Dan. <hi>11.35.</hi>
               </note> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie therefore as <hi>ſchiſmes</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> and <hi>ſpurres,</hi> that <hi>they which are approued might bee made manifeſt; and the ſlothfull in buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, more feruent in ſpirit, ſeruing the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after <hi>Theodoret,</hi> Affliction is the <hi>Hoſtorie,</hi> or<note n="*" place="margin">Strickle.</note> 
               <hi>Stichel</hi> of God in the hand of his <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> with which he ſtriketh off, in his choſen veſſels, the ſins, that againſt <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> his <hi>mercie</hi> cannot beare. <hi>The gracious Lord</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>vſing a balance and a
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:17891:55"/> meaſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theod. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hiſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>compoſed of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Mercie, ſtriketh off here, by his Iuſtice, the faults which are aboue weight and meaſure.</hi> Is any among you afflicted? let the afflicted among you looke vnto the Lord, who doth it <hi>for their good;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to ſtrike off with the hand of his <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> or that rod in his hand on them, the ſinnes, which in them, ſurpoiſe the ſealed ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and ſurpaſſe the marked meaſure of his mercie. Moreouer, <hi>know yee not,</hi> that in the <hi>loweſt condition</hi> is found the <hi>beſt ſucceſſe?</hi> Had not <hi>Iacob,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:17891:55"/> Ioſeph, Dauid,</hi> in the <hi>win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of their affliction,</hi> the <hi>ſpring of the ſoule?</hi> Is not <hi>Gaius</hi> his proſperitie, which is of the ſoule, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than that <hi>of fooles,</hi> which is not<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 23.5.</note> or is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in <hi>Salomons</hi> iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but extreme <hi>vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> and <hi>vexation of ſpirit,</hi> or an euident token of perdition and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? <hi>As the greateſt tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to feele no tentation, ſo the greateſt affliction, not to be afflicted:</hi> An argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of infirmitie, not of maturitie; of infancie, not of manhood. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of outward <hi>beauties</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:17891:56"/> to the Church of the Iewes, were confined to the nonage thereof; grown vpto ſome height, what promiſes of great things?<note place="margin">Duo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d te attrahunt Dei oculos, &amp;c. Fon. ſec. vbi ſup.</note> Two things there be that draw the eyes of God vnto men, <hi>Humble and prompt obedience; Preſſure and perſecution:</hi> Of that <hi>Abraham;</hi> of this an inſtance Iſrael in Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt. <hi>An heart trembling at the word of God; a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humble ſpirit,</hi> doth the like: Suffering, doth a man tremble at the word? <hi>The Lord looketh to him, Iſa.</hi> 66.3. Is hee of a contrite and humble
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:17891:56"/> ſpirit? the high and loftie one that inhabiteth eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, dwelleth with him to reuiue his ſpirit, and to reuiue his heart, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.15. <hi>Deadneſſe</hi> a ſore euill, and <hi>dulneſſe</hi> the graue of many graces, after ſome ioyes conceiued, afflict ſometimes the <hi>Choſen ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Pet, 2.3.</note>. CAVSES; either ſorrow, or exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue care, or obliquitie in the vſe of the meanes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of God, to ſtrengthen the ſoule in the <hi>houre of tentation,</hi> or temporarie deſertion; or elſe the commiſſion of ſome ſin, or the omiſſion of ſome
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:17891:57"/> good dutie, or elſe ſome other ſubtill <hi>deuice of the Deuill;</hi> but CVRATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ONS, or Remedies, none better know I, than <hi>feare and trembling, contrition and humilitie;</hi> for from ſuch the Lord is not far, but at hand, to reuiue them, and wearie with labouring vnder the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie croſſe,</hi> to giue them <hi>happie reſt. For a ſmall mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he forſaketh, but with great mercie he gathereth</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 54.5, 6, 7, 8.</note>. <hi>In a little wrath he hideth his face for a moment, but with euerlaſting kindneſſe he hath mercie on them, that</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a wife of yout<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>are
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:17891:57"/> betrothed vnto him</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Hoſ. 2.19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>in righteouſneſſe, and in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in mercies.</hi> Haue I made a ſtep out of the way? Suppoſe it was to call on a friend.<note place="margin">☜</note> 
               <hi>The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſufferings are not ſo grieuous, as the internall are, and without the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall the externall are not effectuall vnto ſound humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation.</hi> Therefore expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent both, both alſo light, and but for a moment: <hi>The ſufferings of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 8.18. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, ſtyled; <hi>and a kinde of leuitie</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth,</hi> as it commeth, <hi>in the twinckling of an eye:</hi> or
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:17891:58"/> ſtaying all night the acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall <hi>mourning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rico prate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riens leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas. Bez.</note> ioy commeth in the <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 30.5.</note>. A reioycing <hi>is created</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 65.18.</note> yea <hi>appointed</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that mourne in Sion<note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 61.3.</note>, beautie giuen for aſhes, the oyle of ioy for mourning, the garment of praiſe for the ſpirit of heauineſſe, power for faintneſſe, ſtrength for weakneſſe<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 40.29.</note>, the humbled lifted vp<note n="b" place="margin">Iam. 4.10.</note>, the ruined places builded,<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zek. 36.34, 35, 36, 38.</note> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate planted, the deſart villages augmented, and the waſte Cities filled with flocks of men as in the ſolemne aſſemblies.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:17891:58"/>
            <p>Wherefore,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 3.1. <hi>Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Holy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, partakers of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly calling,</hi> I beſeech you ſuffer the word of exhortation<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 13.22.</note>; for yee ſee your ſtate, and the <hi>condition</hi> of this life; how ſeaſoned it is; or may be to you, in the <hi>time and ſeaſon, which the Lord hath put in his owne power</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note>. No rod now vpon you; yet ſcourged ye may be, and be called from aboue to ſuffer <hi>many things:</hi> what yee know not, nor know I when: <hi>God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when and what.</hi> Who maketh you to differ from other <hi>of the royall
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:17891:59"/> prieſthood</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note> Other ſuffer to bee viuified thereby, why not yee? Other ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to be ſanctified there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, why not yee? Other ſuffer to be purged there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, why not yee? Other ſuffer to bee preuented thereby, why not yee? Other ſuffer, and the Lord by their ſufferings is glorified in his <hi>power and prouidence,</hi> by their <hi>faith and obedience,</hi> why not by yours?</p>
            <p>I will not reproue you, for doe yee that ſtand ſafe on the ſhore, on the dry banks, on the high rocks, reioyce againſt other
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:17891:59"/> weather-beaten at ſea, <hi>driuen with fierce winds,</hi> and toſſed with ſwelling waues, or caſt ouer boord and ſwimming for their liues? <hi>They doe verie ill that doe thus</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pro. 17.5.</note> He that is glad of calamitie ſhall not bee vnpuniſhed, nor held innocent. Better were it for you, <hi>to weepe with them that weepe</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 12.15.</note> to ſuffer with them that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, to beare their bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then<note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 6.2</note>, to communicate with their affliction: <hi>To this I will exhort you;</hi> for in doing this yee ſhall doe well. Ye haue done well (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) that yee
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:17891:60"/> did communicate<note n="i" place="margin">Phil. 4.14.</note> with my affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction.</p>
            <p>I will not conuent, nor ſummon you to correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for doe yee deſpiſe any chaſtiſement? doe yee kicke againſt pricks?<note n="k" place="margin">Act 9.5.</note> and the yoke on your necks, ſtiffe-necked are yee as<note n="l" place="margin">Ier. 31.18.</note> Bullocks vnac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to the yoke? are your faces harder than a rocke? doe yee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to returne? <hi>They doe verie ill, that doe thus:</hi> This an aggrauation of the offence and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; yea, two great e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils are perpetrated ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: <hi>Better were it for you
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:17891:60"/> to ſhrinke vnder the mighty hand of God,</hi> and to kiſſe his rod vpon you, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe your faults, and aske him forgiueneſſe, to conuert from the errour of your wayes, and to bring forth fruit meet for repentance. <hi>To this I will exhort you,</hi> for in doing this, yee ſhall haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<note n="m" place="margin">Pro. 28.13.</note>, bee ſaued from the wrath<note n="n" place="margin">Iam. 4.10. &amp; 5.20.</note>, receiued and reconciled, refreſhed and certified, that the Lord hath corrected you <hi>with iudgement,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Ier. 10.24.</note> 
               <hi>not in anger,</hi> not in furie to kill you<note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.25.</note> (as <hi>Heli's</hi> ſonnes;) but <hi>(as Ephraim his deare ſon)</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:17891:61"/>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Ier. 31.20.</note> in loue to reclaime you.</p>
            <p>I will not argue you, that yee ſuffer as <hi>euill do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> or as <hi>buſie-bodies,</hi> or ſlight the ſurpriſall of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, or ſecure your ſelues in <hi>the mount of this worlds good, and the arme of fleſh. They doe verie ill that doe thus,</hi> as they in the <hi>prouocation:</hi> who would wilfully prouoke the Lord, <hi>who doth not from his heart,</hi> or not willingly grieue and <hi>afflict the children of men</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iam. 3.3.</note>? Beſides, the troubles on other men <hi>happen vnto them for enſamples,</hi> and may ſerue <hi>for your admonition</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.6.11.</note>. Yea,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:17891:61"/> they are <hi>your examples,</hi> to the intent yee ſhould not luſt after euill things, as they peraduenture lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted; And will a man neglect ſo faire exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples? Beſides this, the preſent peace, health, and wealth is but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentanie and tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: what man is he that truſteth therein? <hi>Better were it for you,</hi> to bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies cautious<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 3.12.</note>, <hi>leſt there bee in any of you an euill heart of vnebeleefe depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the liuing God,</hi> to be warned by the fals, or harmes of other men, and to caſt away all <hi>confidence
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:17891:62"/> in the fleſh,</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 3.3.</note> leaning <hi>to the, Lord, not to your owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pro. 3 5.</note>. <hi>To this I will exhort you,</hi> for in doing this, yee may keepe your feet, from <hi>euerie euill way,</hi> dwell in ſafetie, lodge in <hi>the ſecret place of the moſt high,</hi> and abide vnder the ſhadow of the Almighty.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 91.1.</note>What ſhall I more ſay? but (as yet haue been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed) <hi>afflicted</hi> or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrable, rememner your, <hi>affliction,</hi> and your miſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: Commit <hi>your way,</hi> and the <hi>keeping of your ſoules in well doing vnto God: pray alwayes: poſſeſſe your ſoules in patience: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:17891:62"/> to the end,</hi> and in the end bee ſaued. The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent guſts and tempeſts purge <hi>the floore of God;</hi> therefore purged; be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged, euen thorowly purged, and truly ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; not touching the vncleane,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.17.</note> nor being (as ſome be) audacious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, and preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>partakers in ether mens ſinnes</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22.</note>.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendo, <hi>2</hi> Conticen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, <hi>3</hi> Conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendo, <hi>4</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiendo, <hi>5</hi> Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo. V. Zanch. in Epheſ. <hi>5.7.11.</hi>
               </note> The preſent afflictions are ſpurre-rowels for vſe, therefore afflicted ſore, bee ſtirred vp eaſily, to follow more earneſtly <hi>the thing that good is.</hi> Suſpect nothing more than the <hi>aduerſitie
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:17891:63"/> of the ſoule,</hi> in the <hi>proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the bodie:</hi> and in the <hi>ſpring of the ſpirit,</hi> which is <hi>the winter of the fleſh,</hi> put forth <hi>the expected fruit of the ſpirit:</hi> or if any dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, if any dulneſſe bee <hi>in the winter of the ſpirit,</hi> bee not diſmayd, neither pleaſe your ſelues there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but rouze vp your ſelues, as thoſe, which being drowzie, are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to ſhake off ſleepe. Call vpon God, and to minde his faithfulneſſe. <hi>Returned to his place</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hoſ. 5 vlt.</note> for ſome ſpeciall end; in the end hee will returne, and <hi>ordaine peace</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 26.12.</note>, and worke
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:17891:63"/> all your works in you, for you. <hi>Faithfull is hee that promiſeth, who will alſo doe it</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.24.</note>. Doe it hee will for you, <hi>inquired of</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ezek. 36.37.</note> by you, to doe it for you. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as he at <hi>Ziglag</hi> great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtreſſed: <hi>Encourage your ſelues in the Lord your God,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.6.</p>
            <p>Hitherto <hi>Dauids condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> hath brought vs, and forth theſe things: fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth <hi>his conſolation,</hi> The word of God, <hi>This is my comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My comfort:<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 87.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> As of <hi>the Citie of God,</hi> many <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious things</hi> are ſpoken of <hi>the word:</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:17891:64"/> woman</hi> all the other <hi>daughters</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 31.29,</note>, this excelleth all. Help in time of need moſt comfortable, and comfort in affliction moſt needfull. This by the word: Therefore we conclude:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That the word of God, is the beſt comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Comfortable at the raine vnto the tender</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Deut. 32.2.</note> 
               <hi>herbs, and as ſhowers to the graſſe, ſweet as honey</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 119.72.127.103.</note> 
               <hi>and the honey combe; eſteemed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the appointed food</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iob. 13.12</note>, <hi>more deſired than gold, yea then much fine gold</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal 19.10</note>, <hi>and as much as in all riches re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyced in</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 119.14.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="117" facs="tcp:17891:64"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Is it not pure,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.</note> 
               <hi>is it not perfect,</hi> ſure and ſound, durable and delightfull, moſt holy and moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie?</p>
            <p>Doth it not <hi>conuert,</hi> or <hi>returne the ſoule,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 19.7.</note> being in a ſwoune, ouercome with the preſent maladie, or miſerie, and make it come againe?</p>
            <p>Doth it not <hi>quicken</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 19.50.</note>, is it not <hi>the life</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Deut. 32.47.</note>, euen <hi>The word of life</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 5.20.</note>? <hi>liue wee by bread</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 4.4.</note>, or thereby? Is it not the ſeed and food of life, <hi>milke</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.2</note> 
               <hi>and ſtrong meat?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth it not vanquiſh <hi>the wicked one</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Io. 2.14.</note>, bruize his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:17891:65"/> head and him vnder foot? Is it not a <hi>ſword</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pro. 30.5.</note> to wound <hi>his ſcalpe,</hi> and a <hi>ſhield</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> to quench all his fierie darts?</p>
            <p>Doth it not <hi>reioyce the heart</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 19.7, 8.</note>, make wiſe the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, enlighten the eyes, enrich the poore<note n="y" place="margin">Coloſ 3.16.</note>, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie euerie creature<note n="z" place="margin">1 Tim 4.5.</note>, keepe from ſinne<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 119.11.</note>, heale the diſeaſed<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 107.20.</note>, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the afflicted?</p>
            <p>This the report from Heauen of the Word, which is ſettled for euer<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> in Heauen.</p>
            <p>But a voyce is heard in the lower <hi>Ramah's, the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ezek. 47.11.</note> 
               <hi>and mariſhes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:17891:65"/> to ſalt, and not healed</hi> by the riuers of waters which flow from the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie.</hi> Giue vs, for our comfort, <hi>the honours of the world, the treaſures of the earth, the pleaſures of this life, potent friends, and lets continue in our ſinnes:</hi> This our comfort and theſe: Oh, what comfort in theſe againſt the word, or without the word, with <hi>All that is in they world?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. What comfort in the honors of the world?<note place="margin">Honores mundi, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di. Eucher.</note> the honors of the world, the tumors thereof, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors and burthens, <hi>not
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:17891:66"/> of God; not of God, the word of God not with them:</hi> Conſider what is ſaid in <hi>Iob.</hi> 10.35. Gods they, or Infidels rather, vnto whom the word com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not? How can they beleeue, which receiue honour one of another<note n="e" place="margin">Io. 5.44.</note>, and ſeeke not the honour that commeth from God only in the comming of the word? How doe they beleeue, <hi>which loue the praiſe of men</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Io. 12.43.</note> 
               <hi>more than the praiſe of God?</hi> How doe they beleeue that haue not, nor hold forth<note n="g" place="margin">Phil. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>the word of life?</hi> This the <hi>Beraeans</hi> had, the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:17891:66"/> that: Who beſt? yet glorious they are, and honoured, wee ſee; but know wee not, that their glorie is their ſhame<note n="h" place="margin">Phil. 3.19.</note>, their excellencie their ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominie, and their end obſcuritie? <hi>Ierome</hi> not amiſſe to his riſing and aſpiring friend,<note place="margin">Hier. ep. <hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Its ſafer to ſtand on the firme earth, than to ſit high on a rotten ſcaffold.</hi> Vanitie of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, <hi>vanitie of vanities:</hi> what elſe is all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the world.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What comfort, without the Word, in the treaſures of the earth? The treaſures of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:17891:67"/> earth, <hi>melting ſnow-balls</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob 38.22.</hi> Greg. in loc.</note>, ſwift flying<note n="k" place="margin">Pro. 23.5.</note> Eagles, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine<note n="l" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.17.</note>, deceitfull<note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 13.12.</note>, ſtrong Cities razed, and high towers demoliſhed in a moment, Idols, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dals,<note n="n" place="margin">Ezek. 7.19.</note> 
               <hi>ſtumbling blocks of iniquitie, leaders into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, fooliſh and hurtfull luſts. They that will be rich</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.9.</note> fall fouly. They that <hi>truſt in their wealth, and boaſt themſelues in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their riches</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 49.6, 7, 8, 11, 12, 13.</note>, <hi>none of them can by any meanes redeeme his brother, nor giue to God a ranſome for his ſoule;</hi> neither for their owne. Their inward thought is folly, as their
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:17891:67"/> way, and howbeit their poſteritie may approue their ſayings, as their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, as men wiſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh; yet bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh they are, and <hi>like the beaſts which periſh.</hi> Their riches ſhall choke them, for they choke the good ſeed of the Word<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 13.22.</note> or ſwallowed downe, they ſhall vomit them vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,<note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 20.15 18.</note> 
               <hi>God ſhall caſt them out of their bellies:</hi> Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, verily, this egeſtion will be wofull, and full of deadly paines. Therfore, <hi>Goe to now, yee rich men</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Iam. 5.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>weepe and howle for the miſeries which ſhall come
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:17891:68"/> vpon you; your riches are corrupted, your gold and ſiluer is cankered, and the ruſt of them ſhall bee a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt you, and eat your fleſh as it were fire; yee heape treaſure together for the laſt dayes:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 2.5.</note> yea, <hi>yee treaſure vp wrath vnto your ſelues againſt the day of wrath:</hi> Faithfull, but fearefull is the ſaying of Ieſus Chriſt in <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.23. <hi>A rich man ſhall hardly enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heauen.</hi> A diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie noted, not an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilitie; for after the <hi>Ordinarie Gloſſe,</hi> a Gable, <hi>i.</hi> vntwiſted; a Camell
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:17891:68"/> alſo <hi>(Depoſito onere &amp; flexis genibus)</hi> may goe thorow that ſtrait gate in the wals of Hieruſalem, which for the narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof was called <hi>Foramen acus,</hi> or the Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles eye: But wealth, a <hi>ſtrong City</hi> in conceit, and an high Tower, (as it is the rich mans, that is not rich towards God, <hi>Prou.</hi> 18.11. and <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.21. compared;) the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilitie may be auou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and auerred.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What comfort in the pleaſures of this life, the pleaſures of this life flaſhes of lightning:
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:17891:69"/> Fulgurations;<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <hi>Simul ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes &amp; morientes,</hi> ariſing and dying together. As the faſhion of the world,<note place="margin">—<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpia do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas.</note> they paſſe away, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth heauineſſe;<note n="f" place="margin">Pro. 14.13.</note> caſt out into vtter darkneſſe, what weeping, what howling, what gnaſhing with the teeth? <hi>Dead, while they liue, they that liue in pleaſure</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.6.</note>. Ye haue <hi>liued in pleaſure,</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iam. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>and been wanton,</hi> an apt reproofe. <hi>Awake to righteouſneſſe</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.34.</note>, good counſell. <hi>Moſes</hi> his patterne good<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 11.25.</note>, <hi>Barzil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la's</hi> reſolution godly<note n="l" place="margin">2 Sam. 19.35.</note>, the Preachers cenſure of mirth and laughter iuſt<note n="m" place="margin">Eccl. 2.2.</note>,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17891:69"/> carnall pleaſure the high way to Hell, <hi>going down to the chambers of death</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pro. 8.27.</note>. Had here in the depths of hell, what is to bee had? Aske <hi>Abraham,</hi> or thinke on his anſwer<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk. 16.25.</hi> —Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hit ſua quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> voluptas.</note>, bought with griefe, yet how many drawen away thereby and inticed? As hee that loueth ſiluer, ſo is he that loueth pleaſure,<note place="margin">Semper vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mem ſui ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acta non ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial. Hieron.</note> neuer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, not euer edified on the moſt holy faith. The voluptuous of the word heard, bring no fruit to perfection<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 8.14</note>. Was <hi>Salomon</hi> a Cynicke in his old age? Faithfull is his ſaying, and worthy of all
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:17891:70"/> acceptation, <hi>Sorrow is better than laughter</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.3, 4.</note>; for by the ſadneſſe of the countenance, the heart is made better: The heart of the wiſe is in the houſe of mourning, but the heart of fooles is in the houſe of mirth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What comfort in carnall friends? Friends as the <hi>reeds of Aegypt,</hi> or as reeds in the wind, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; vnſtable as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous Mammon. No friend this, <hi>for a friend lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth at all times</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pro. 17.17. &amp; cap. 18.24.</note>, and in aduerſitie moſt. <hi>A bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> rather <hi>a rare friend,</hi> one that ſticks faſt, as ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:17891:70"/> or glued.<note place="margin">V. Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright in loc.</note> I haue conſidered that in <hi>Prou.</hi> 18.24. but all are not <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri amicoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> nor haue <hi>vim amicabilem.</hi> As friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe is ſhewed, ſo is it to be ſhewed; but as it is ſound, ſo lieth the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>The colours of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip not laid in the oyle of the word, a falſe varniſh;</hi> it vaniſheth <hi>as the tale that is told:</hi> Wherefore what the Holy Ghoſt hath of worldly wealth, might be ſaid of worldly friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Hee that truſteth therein ſhall fall<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pro. 11.28.</note>. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, a curſe is denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,<note n="t" place="margin">Ier. 17.5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed is the man
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:17891:71"/> that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his arme, and whoſe heart departeth from the Lord; for hee ſhall bee like the heath in the deſart, like the parched places in the wilderneſſe, like a ſalt land, and not inhabited.</hi> Therefore the ſweet Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt of Iſrael ſaid<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 146.3, 4.</note>, <hi>Put not your truſt in Princes, nor in the ſonne of man, in whom there is no helpe, his breath goeth forth, he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to his earth, in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie day his thoughts periſh.</hi> But <hi>Wolſey's</hi> confeſſion might<note n="x" place="margin">Quod Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi potius quam Deo ſtuduiſſet placere. Scultet. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> be made of many; <hi>Many ſeeke the friendſhip of great men, more than the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:17891:71"/> fauour of the great God, and our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt:</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.5.15.25.</note> 
               <hi>Iſtos auerſemur: From ſuch turne away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. What comfort to be had in ſinnes? Miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comforters theſe, and cauſes of confuſion; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah's</hi> in conceit, in effect alſo, deceiuing the heart, deſtroying the ſoule. Bleſſe a man may him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his owne heart, ſaying, <hi>I ſhall haue peace, though I walk in the imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of mine own heart, to adde drunkennes to thirſt</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Deut. 20.19.</note>. But, <hi>There is no peace to the wicked,</hi> ſaith my God<note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 51.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note>. At the doore of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:17891:72"/> lieth his ſinne<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 4.7.</hi> Peccatum i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ana pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti quae quaſi ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it aut Cerberus cub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, fores peccati ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidet tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati vindex. Corn. de lap. in loc.</note>, as a ban-dog, to plucke out his throat, and to teare him in peeces, none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deliuer: Who ſhould, the Lord? Nay, he is not choſen, nor hath beene ſerued; but ſinne preferred; let him <hi>goe that and cry</hi> vnto that which hee hath choſen, and to that which hee hath ſerued. This was once the anſwer of the Lord, and this: I will deliuer no more<note n="z" place="margin">Iudg. 10.13, 14.</note>, who then ſhould? ſhould the Miniſter of the Lord? By what meanes, the Miniſterie contemned<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.18.</note>,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:17891:72"/> which is committed to him? viſit he may a man ſicke with ſin vnto death, yet not ſaue him from the death, which reigneth by ſinne in his mortall members; pray for him he may, but according to that of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſius,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Si dignus non ſum qui a te au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diar, nec etiam dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus qui pro te a Deo ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udiar.</note> 
               <hi>If he will not heare the Miniſter ſpeaking from God, how ſhall God heare the Miniſter ſpeaking for him.</hi> O conſider this, all yee that comfort your ſelues in your ſinnes, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing inconſiderately the multitude that doe euill, after theſe of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, dayes of mourning
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:17891:73"/> will come, and euill daies, yea yeares, wherein wee ſhall ſay, <hi>Wee haue no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in them</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1.</note>, nor any comfort from the time that is paſt. What com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the time that is paſt of this life, the luſts of men followed, and thwarted the will of God<note n="b" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.2.</note>? What comfort in thoſe things, whereof ſhame is the glorie, and deſtruction the end<note n="e" place="margin">Phil. 3.19</note>? Whats the end of rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, drunkenneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, idleneſſe, vnruli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, vncleanneſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe? or whats the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:17891:73"/> glorie? What fruit had in theſe things<note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 6.21.</note> or what comfort to be had,<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iudge I pray you betweene God, and the vines which bring forth wilde grapes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art thou, ô man, an Ephraimite<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 28.1.</note>, a drunkard, I meane like thoſe of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim,</hi> riſeſt thou vp ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the morning, that thou maieſt follow ſtrong drinke, and continueſt thou vntill night, till wine purſue thee? Art thou mightie to drinke wine, and a man of ſtrength to mingle ſtrong drinke<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 5.11, 22.</note>? Woe and woe I finde, yea woes vpon woes in the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:17891:74"/> Scriptures againſt thee<note n="h" place="margin">Hab. 2.15</note>, but except thou repent, <hi>no comfort finde I for thee in the Oracles of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art thou a couetous perſon, a louer of earthly things more than of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly, is thy heart ſet on <hi>thy riches increaſing,</hi> is thy deſire inlarged as Hell<note n="i" place="margin">Hab. 2.5.</note>, can it not bee ſatisfied? <hi>Thou ſhalt neuer be ſatisfied</hi> with that which thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereſt; thou conſulteſt, (by coueting an euill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe to thy houſe) <hi>ſhame to thy houſe,</hi> thou ſinneſt <hi>againſt thine owne ſoule</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Hab. 2.9, 10.</note>: Thou art an Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>later, and abhorred of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:17891:74"/> the Lord: Theſe things I finde in the Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, but except thou repent; <hi>No comfort finde I in the Oracles of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art thou a ſwearer, ſweareſt thou in thine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie communication? Thou takeſt the name of thy God in vaine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuit. 24.11.</hi> Nakab defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens tranſ. figens. V. Trem.</note> thou ſmiteſt him on the face: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith more, Thou pierceſt him, thou ſtrikeſt him thorow. Hee that blaſphemeth, traiecteth him whom hee blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth; and as the lying or backe-biting tongue hateth thoſe that are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:17891:75"/> by it<note n="l" place="margin">Pro. 26.28.</note>, ſo the ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tongue the Lord. Thou champeſt the bloud of God betweene thy teeth, ô barbarous Caniball! Thou diggeſt vp his wounds, ô damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exulteration! Thou expoſeſt him to ſhame, ô impudent Miſcreant! Thou art not guiltleſſe<note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 20.7.</note>, but curſing, curſed: The curſe is vpon thee, and entred into thy houſe. The long flying roll<note n="n" place="margin">Zech. 5.2.5.</note> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereth ouer thee, yea, the vengeance of Heauen to caſt thee downe into the damnation of Hell. Theſe things I finde in the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:17891:75"/> Scriptures againſt thee, but except thou repent, <hi>No comfort finde I for thee in the Oracles of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art thou a Sabbath-breaker? ſeekeſt thou on the holy day of God, and findeſt thou thine owne pleaſure, ſpeakeſt thou thine owne words<note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 58.13.</note>, and doeſt thou, on that day, thine owne works? Thou diſhonoureſt God<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 2.23</note>, thou polluteſt his worſhip<note n="q" place="margin">Ezek. 22.8.</note>, thou prouokeſt the eyes of his glorie<note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 3.8.</note>, thou brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt his Law, thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt it void<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 119.126. 2 Chron. 19.2. <hi>A minori ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maius.</hi> Ior. 17.27.</note>; <hi>Therefore wrath is vpon thee, from before the Lord:</hi> The fuell
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:17891:76"/> of iudgement lieth in thy gate, and thou putteſt to the fire, which ſhal (when God will) kindle where it lyeth. Theſe things I finde in the Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, but except thou repent; <hi>No comfort finde I for thee in the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Art thou a Libertine, vſing all libertie for an occaſion to the fleſh<note n="x" place="margin">Gal. 5.13.</note>, a contemner of Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, his words and Sacraments, his Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and Miniſters? Thou art not ſpirituall<note n="y" place="margin">Rom. 7.14. &amp; cap. 8.14.</note>, nor led by the Spirit, but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall altogether, and ſold
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:17891:76"/> vnder ſinne; thou deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt God<note n="z" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.8.</note>, thou commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſacrilege<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 2.22.</note>, thou iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt thy ſelfe vnworthy of euerlaſting life<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 13.46.</note>, thou putteſt from thee the meanes thereof, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt the ſame into laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiouſneſſe<note n="c" place="margin">Iude ve. 4.</note> no remedie remaineth, nor healing to thee that mocketh the Meſſengers of God, that deſpiſeſt his words, that miſuſeſt his Prophets<note n="d" place="margin">2 Chron. 36.16.</note>. Theſe things I finde in the Scriptures againſt thee, but except thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, <hi>No comfort finde I for thee in the Oracles of God.</hi> I perſonate no
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:17891:77"/> man, but if the witneſſe within, the Conſcience, accuſe any, teſtifying and ſaying, <hi>Thou art the man to whom it is ſpoken;</hi> ſpoken bee to him, and this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Spirit of our God againſt the workes of the fleſh, which are manifeſt, and are theſe; <hi>Adulterie, fornication, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe, laſciuiouſneſſe, idolatrie, witchcraft, hatred, variance, emulations, wrath, ſtrife, ſeditions, hereſies, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyings, murthers, drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, reuellings, and ſuch like. Qui talia agunt</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 5 21.</note>, They which doe ſuch things ſhall not inherit
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:17891:77"/> the kingdome of God, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that theſe things are ſo, that ſome comfort themſelues with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Word, and that without the Word there is no ſolid comfort. A neceſſitie is laid vpon vs, both for the vſe of edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the iſſue of the point, to reaſon in plaine euidence and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Spirit,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>De Afflicto conſolabili.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>De Sermone conſolabundo.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>De Ratione conſolandi.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:17891:78"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Touching</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The afflicted that are conſolable.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The word which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forteth the afflicted.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The manner of comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them by the ſame word.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>De afflicto conſolabili. Of the afflicted that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolable. All men haue not faith</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.2.</note>, <hi>nor the knowledge of God</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 15 34.</note>, nor bee in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction comforted <hi>by the Word,</hi> neither indeed can be, becauſe they are not corrigible, not docile, not humble, nor humbled: <hi>The ſhaking of the hand of the Lord, which hee ſhaketh ouer them,</hi> not feared; nor
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:17891:78"/> had to worke any feare in their heart <hi>the ſpirit of bondage.</hi> But had once this, and but once had, <hi>Running there is to God, and flying to Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out back-ſliding in heart, or any departing from him: <hi>Contrà:</hi> Not hand, nor receiued at all, no comfort at all, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion at all, neither any conſtant worſhip. In <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. <hi>Yee haue not receiued the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage againe to feare.</hi> Not to feare againe as bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaues, but firſt they fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, hauing the <hi>ſpirit of bondage,</hi> as all haue that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:17891:79"/> labour and are heauie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, the curſes of the Law may be denounced a thouſand times, and ten thouſand kinds of ſtrong iudgements inflicted in vaine, except the ſpirit of bondage be ſent into the heart, to worke feare therein, and in that feare to bring men home vnto God in Chriſt. Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and raine, and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes haue beene, and yet mens hearts haue beene little moued, but the ſpirit of bondage,<note place="margin">D. Preſton of the new Couenant. pag. 392, 393.</note> or of feare on the people, they feared exceedingly, <hi>when it thundred and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:17891:79"/> in wheat harueſt</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">1 Sam. 12 18.</note>, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at the great ſhowres of raine in <hi>Ezra's</hi> time<note n="i" place="margin">Ezra. 10.9.</note>, likewiſe the Iaylor, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though all was ſafe<note n="k" place="margin">Act. 16.29</note>. This ſpirit, the plough of God, with which hee ploweth vp the heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee ſoweth therein the word of his grace which bringeth ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: This ſpirit oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates the image of the old man, and prepares a place for the impreſſe of the new, whoſe motto is,<note n="l" place="margin">Pro. 28.14</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth alwayes, i.</hi> in a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall manner, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile is the Deuils.</p>
            <pb n="148" facs="tcp:17891:80"/>
            <p>Ye ſee the reaſon, (bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) why ſome affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted are not conſolable; not conſolable,<note place="margin">Actus acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um eſt in patiente pradiſpoſito.</note> not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible; not corrigible, not fearing; not fearing, not hauing to feare, <hi>the ſprit of bondage.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if yee feare not, nor haue had to feare, <hi>the ſpirit of bondage.</hi> Yee haue cauſe to feare, becauſe ye haue not Chriſt,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> yee know him not, nor what hee hath ſuffered for you, yee haue no <hi>fellowſhip in his ſufferings, not being made conformable to his death:</hi> But afflicted, if ye feare as <hi>ſonnes in bondage,</hi>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:17891:80"/> if feeling the weight of the iudgement inflicted, and ſeeing your ſinnes, yee flie from them (as from the <hi>face of a ſerpent</hi>) vnto the <hi>Propitiatorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. 3.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Io. 16. vlt.</note> which is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> Be of good cheere, the good ſpirit of God is vpon you for good, and truly and thorowly humbled there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, yee ſhall be deliuered from the temporall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, into <hi>the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the ſonnes of God. As the Law is good, Rom.</hi> 7.12. ſo <hi>the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage:</hi> As the Law but a temporarie <hi>Schoole-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> vntill faith bee infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:17891:81"/> ſo <hi>the ſpirit of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage,</hi> vntill <hi>the ſpirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption</hi> be infuſed: and as the <hi>Sunne of righteouſneſſe</hi> ariſeth <hi>with healing in his wings, Mal.</hi> 4.2. So the Spirit of adoption com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth with libertie <hi>in his armes.</hi> God hauing ſent <hi>the ſpirit of his ſonne into the hearts</hi> of his ſonnes, they cry <hi>Abba, father</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note>: the loue of an <hi>indulgent father</hi> apprehended, not the ſeueritie of an <hi>auſtere Iudge;</hi> and God beheld not as a <hi>conſuming fire</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 4.24.</note>, that will deuoure them, but as <hi>a faithfull Creator,</hi> that will haue a deſire to
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:17891:81"/> the workes of his hands<note n="o" place="margin">Iob 14.15</note>. Afterwards there's no <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile,</hi> but <hi>a filiall feare, i.</hi> a mixture of feare and loue: <hi>the ſpirit of loue lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the way euerlaſting; the ſpirit of feare</hi> preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Reconciliation,</hi> and fetching home againe them, that being brought home, <hi>turne againe vnto folly,</hi> loſe themſelues, and runne as ſheepe aſtray. <hi>Loue hauing reſpect vnto all the Commandements,</hi> to keepe the ſame: <hi>feare</hi> preſeruing the heart from the deceitfulneſſe of ſin: for as feething liquor, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>um; ſo the heart
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:17891:82"/> boyling with feare, caſts out ſinne, ſuffers it not to oeſtuate it ſelfe into the inward parts; adhere it may, but enters not into the frame, fabricke, or conſtitution of the heart, to bee mingled and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded: <hi>The feare of the Lord is cleane</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 19.9.</note>, they alſo <hi>pure in heart,</hi> that haue it in their heart, hauing ſuch an heart, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits not the mixture of any ſin, but as baſe and reprobate ſtuffe, reſiſts and reiects it. So then we ſay for the <hi>verdict of the Inqueſt; That without the humbling and cleanſing
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:17891:82"/> feare, there's no token for good in or out of affliction, nor comfort by the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>De Sermone conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torio:</hi> Of the word which is the comfort in Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The ſubſtantiall Word there is, that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which was made fleſh<note n="q" place="margin">Io. 1.14.</note>, and hee the God<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 15.5.</note> of all conſolation: but of him the Prophet ſpeaketh not here, the ſure word of prophecie there is alſo, which was vnto <hi>Ieremie,</hi> hauing found and eaten it, the verie ioy and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of his heart<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ier. 15.16.</note>, <hi>Dauid</hi> made his heart an hiding place for it<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 119, 11.</note> ſo became it
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:17891:83"/> a Sanctuarie for him, yea, a fortreſſe againſt the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of Satan, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the obſeſſion, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition for his ſoule.<note n="u" place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.11.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (as the Apoſtle of Chriſt) All and in all: Therefore ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Sermo</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Inſcriptus,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>&amp; Inſititius.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Many good words and comfortable words in the little Booke which we hold in our hand, but the word which comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth is,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Inſcribed Word.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>The Ingrafted Word.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:17891:83"/>1. <hi>Sermo inſcriptus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sermo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolatorius inſcriptus ſermo.</note> The word inſcribed and written, not with inke, but with the ſpirit of the the liuing God<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.3</note>, not in Tables of ſtone, or books like this, but in the fleſhie Tables of the heart; the heart mollified the ſpirit ſent into it, which wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth therein the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting word, euen the word of grace in the New Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, <hi>i.</hi> worketh within the heart a diſpoſition correſpondent <hi>to the word which commeth</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Io. 10.35.</note>, <hi>and the grace which appeareth</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note>. As face to face in a glaſſe, or in the waters, as
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:17891:84"/> Tally to Tally, as Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Indenture, as the Impreſſion in the Wax to the Seale that made the ſame, ſo the holy diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which is, <hi>The Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation</hi>) anſwereth to the word, which is in the heart written, yea grauen by the ſpirit of God, as letters in marble, neuer wearing out. Let a man therefore examine him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and brethren, proue your owne ſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch a diſpoſition and correſpondence to the Word be in you, yea or no? If your heart and the word meet as friends,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:17891:84"/> euen as mercie and truth, and kiſſe each other as righteouſneſſe &amp; peace<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note>. If your heart cloſe with the word, as the clay with the mold, and the inke to the paper, fixt and faire, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any blurre or foule fault, quarrell or diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: It is <hi>inſcribed,</hi> it is the word which comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in affliction; but if enmitie be put betweene, or if your heart and the word looke as enemies the one vpon the other, no comfort is therein, nor in the affliction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Sermo inſititius, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:17891:85"/> conſolatorius:</hi> The <hi>word of conſolation, S. Iames</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>the ingrafted word</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iam. 1.21. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, which when <hi>Paul</hi> plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.6</note>, he cleanſeth, 1. the ſtocke, 2. maketh inſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 3. inſerteth the impe, 4. cloſeth it about, 5. fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth it, finally expecteth fruit. Suffer me to reuiew and open theſe vnto you, that your eyes opened by the euidence produced, yee may ſee the things, <hi>that pertaine to your peace,</hi> in your warfare on the earth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The ſtocke, which is the heart, is to bee clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, foule it is in all, all
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:17891:85"/> filthineſſe and ſuperfluitie of naughtineſſe about it, which is to be laid aſide<note n="d" place="margin">Iam. 1.21.</note>, with all malice, and all guile, and hypocriſies, and enuies, and euill ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings<note n="e" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2</note>, or elſe the ſincere word will bee turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. If the ſtomack riſe, &amp; the ſoule bee lifted vp<note n="f" place="margin">Hab. 2.4.</note>, when the heauenly huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman, about to plant the word, is about to purge the ſtocke. If any rancor or excreſcencie of malice, bitterneſſe, and wrath, and anger, and cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour be;<note n="g" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.31.</note> 
               <hi>Now hee ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mee, he intendeth mee, hee cutteth mee, who can
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:17891:86"/> heare him, who can endure him? Aërem coedit,</hi> Hee beateth the aire, hee wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the Aethiopian, his labour is in vaine. Cut to the heart ye know, who were with the words of <hi>Stephen,</hi> and to what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 7.54.</note> who were pricked and healed by the ſame Word receiued with meekneſſe, ye alſo know<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 2 37.</note> verily, as the Apoſtle of him that praying waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth like a waue of the ſea, driuen with the wind and toſſed:<note n="k" place="margin">Iam. 1.6, 7.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Let not that man thinke that hee ſhall receiue any thing of the
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:17891:86"/> Lord: So may we of the man, that hearing the word, and hauing it nigh him, paring, or pricking, or cutting, or cleauing him, to bee ingrafted in him, is like the troubled ſea, when it cannot reſt, whoſe waters caſt vp mire and dirt,<note n="l" place="margin">Iſa. 57.20.</note> is moued, wexeth angrie, flingeth it off in furie, and kicketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt pricks, <hi>Non exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met homo ille,</hi> Let not that man think that the word ſhall bee, or poſſiblie can be in him, doing thus, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually ingrafted: <hi>Qui aurem audiendi habet,</hi> He that hath an eare to heare
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:17891:87"/> let him heare, and heare yee it my beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, if yee would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ingrafted word for your comfort <hi>in that day, ſanctifie your ſelues, and cleanſe your ſelues from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1.</note>, prepare your heart, or (as <hi>Ieremie</hi> phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it)<note n="n" place="margin">Ier. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>waſh your heart,</hi> from the deſperate wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof: or, <hi>keepe your feet</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>when yee enter into the houſe of God,</hi> and bee more readie to heare the hardeſt word, than to caſt it off as a burthen too heauie for you to beare.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:17891:87"/> Hard as iron is the heart of man; therefore is the word firſt as fire, and an hammer for it<note n="p" place="margin">Ier. 23.29.</note>; full of knots and wilde ſtems, which muſt bee cut off; therefore is the word <hi>ſharper</hi> at the firſt, <hi>than any two-edged ſword</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note>, yet to bee ſuffered without any preiudicate or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaricate opinion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious perſonating, or enuious particularizing; your ſoules (deare Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) muſt (if ye would bee numbred with the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of God, and recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of his peculiar peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) be dealt with in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:17891:88"/> and your particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſinnes reproued, yea hewed and hewed, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag</hi> by <hi>Samuel,</hi> in peeces, before yee can feele any comfort by the word: Many things wee ſpeake in loue, to warne you<note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.14.</note>, not in malice to ſhame you, but the more wee loue you thus<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.15.</note>, the leſſe we are loued of you: wee loue your perſons, wee tender your ſoules; but (as our owne) wee hate your ſinnes, and would (if wee could) ſtrike them dead, becauſe they worke by their paſſions<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 7.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and motions in your mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:17891:88"/> (as in ours) to bring forth fruit to death vnto death.</p>
            <p>But how can a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher ſmite a mans ſinne really, and not touch his perſon intentionally? Our controuerſie writers in that great diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout iuſtifying faith;<note place="margin">D. Abbot againſt Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. pag. 481.</note> 
               <hi>Whether faith iuſtifieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone without charitie and good workes,</hi> diſtinguiſh thus:</p>
            <p>Separation of things, one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, is either real in the ſubiect, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall in the vnderſtanding, that denied, this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhed, negatiue
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:17891:89"/> or priuatiue; that, when in the vnderſtanding there is an affirming of one thing, and denying of another; this, when of things that cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed bee ſeparated, the one is vnderſtood and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted: the other, <hi>ver. grat.</hi> light and heat can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee ſeparated in the fire, yet the light may he conſidered, &amp; not the heat, or the heat and not the light: So charity and good works are not nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely ſeparated, but pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatiuely made as effects &amp; conſequents, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring cauſes of iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
            <pb n="167" facs="tcp:17891:89"/>
            <p>Sembably (my Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) although we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not really ſeparate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene your ſinnes and your perſons, yet nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely we ſay, that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not your perſons, but priuatiuely in our mindes we conſider your ſinnes, bearing the image of Satan, at which wee ſtrike, I ſay at the image of the Deuill and Satan, not at your perſons, made as we our ſelues, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſimilitude of God.</p>
            <p>O that yee would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue this, and when your ſinnes are ſmitten on the face with the rod of the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:17891:90"/> mouth<note n="u" place="margin">Iſa. 11.4.</note>, or with that ſharpe two edged ſword which goeth out of the mouth of the Lord<note n="x" place="margin">Reu. 1.16.</note>, ye would reaſon with your ſelues, or commune with your owne heart, and be ſtill or ſpeake on this wiſe one vnto another in the faithfull aſſemblies: <hi>This Preacher ſpeakes with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aboue himſelfe, its the very word of God which hee preacheth, the word which he preacheth is quicke and powerfull</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note>, <hi>pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth and diuideth things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder in vs, diſcerneth the thoughts and intents of our hearts, pulleth downe ſtrong
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:17891:90"/> holds</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">2 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>caſteth downe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, and euery high thing that exalteth it ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the knowledge of God; apprehendeth our ſins, grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleth with them, euinceth them, conuinceth vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15</note> 
               <hi>dealeth as a workman that needeth not to be aſhamed, rightly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiding the word of truth, &amp; applying it according to the rule thereof. Are wee not our ſelues or many of vs huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, what doe we our ſelues in our profeſsion? doe wee caſt our ſeed into vncleane places, or amongst bryars, &amp; thorns, and ſtones, &amp; rubbiſh no, we firſt clenſe and manure our ground,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:17891:91"/> ſowe afterwards our ſeed, and haue long patience for the precious fruit: beſides, in our orchards, when we plant or graffe, doe we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to grow the fiens of the crab-tree? No, we cut them off, and cleanſe the ſtocke: What then doth the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all husbandman more in his ſpheare, than we in ours; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he will ſowe the holy ſeed, or let in the heauenly plant, hee laboureth with great difficulty to prepare the ground where he would ſowe, and purge the ſtocke on which he would ingraffe the word. Muſt hee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be blamed, or ſlouenly
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:17891:91"/> would we haue him to doe his worke, or negligently, or vnfaithfully? Abſit,</hi> God for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id: <hi>This in our owne ſeruants is not tolerated, much leſſe it to bee in the ſeruants of the Lord</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ier. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>To cry peace, peace, when there is no peace, is to heale hurts ſlightly</hi> *; falſe Prophets will doe it, but otherwiſe, the man that is ſent from God. Conſider what I ſay, and God giue you vnderſtanding. The word to be ingraffed, the ſtock is to bee cleanſed: The ſtocke cleanſed, inciſion for inſition is made; a diuiſion made betweene
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:17891:92"/> the ſoule and the ſpirit<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb. 4.12</hi> Nomen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>timae ſaepe idem valet quod ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; ſed cum ſimul iun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendit ſub ſe affectus omnes, &amp;c. Caluin. in lic. Allegoria quadam &amp; hyperocha <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dumbrare v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>luit Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſermonis vim &amp; effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, &amp;c. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llinger.</note>, <hi>naturall things, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things, reaſon and the light, which is the life of men, the affections and the intellectuall facultie:</hi> This diuiſion Experience rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth <hi>tacitè,</hi> and conuerts beſt know how it is. How were the firſt <hi>pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their hearts,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided in themſelues, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t knowing what to doe<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note>, after the inciſion made, before, before the immiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the heauenly plant? nor doth any man: The word which ſaueth the ſoule, of whom re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued without much
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:17891:92"/> affliction by the internall diuiſion, after the infiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Such it is, I thinke, as the groanings of the Spirit, making interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on according to the will of God, it cannot be vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: the Theſſalonians receiued the word with much affliction, but what kind of affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction, or how grieuous it was, he ſaith not.</p>
            <p>Therefore, whenſoeuer inciſion is made, your heart ſmitten, and ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting you being ſmitten by the word, attend ſtill; or diuided in you ſelues, all the faculties
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:17891:93"/> ſlit, and clouen the affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, your reaſon viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the day-ſpring from on high, your vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding illightened, your ſoule fainting, your ſpirit panting, a confl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct begunne, and a ſtriuing within you, as in <hi>Rebec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cahs</hi> wombe, betweene <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> Nature and Grace. Bee not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied, for this muſt be, and is, where the word is about to bee ingraffed to the ſauing of the ſoule.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Inc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion for inſition made; the ſien of holy ſcience is infited and ſet in, the word let in (that
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:17891:93"/> heauenly plant by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Art) into the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: <hi>The ſenſe giuen thereof, and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnderſtood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore hearing the word of the kingdome, <hi>apply</hi> your heart to wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and your minde to vnderſtand <hi>the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous things</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 119.18.</note> the <hi>myſteries which were kept ſecret ſince the world began</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 16.15.</note> yea, pray alwayes <hi>with all manner of prayer and ſupplication, in the ſpirit,</hi> that it may bee giuen vnto you, to know <hi>the myſterie of God</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Coloſſ. 2 2. 1 Tim. 3.16.</note>, <hi>and of godlineſſe,</hi> that ſeeing yee may ſee, that hearing yee
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:17891:94"/> may heare and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 13.16.</note>; <hi>Dauid</hi> prayed how often? G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue me vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, make me to vnderſtand; An vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding heart, <hi>Salomons</hi> hearts deſire<note n="i" place="margin">Reg. 3.9.</note>; and <hi>Pauls,</hi> that the Churches might abound more and more<note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 1.8, 9.</note> in all knowledge, and in all iudgement, in all wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſpirituall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: This by the Word. The word read or heard, and not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, profiteth not; but by reading, and hearing, and prayer made to God, entrance is made into the vnderſtanding, heauenly
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:17891:94"/> light let in, and worldly darkneſſe out:<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 119, 130,</note> The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the word giueth light, it giueth vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſimple.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The ſien inſited, is bound faſt, and cloſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with all louing affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions ſtirred vp vnto it; yea, ſhut vp and riuetted in the heart, to dwell rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therein in all wiſdom, not left looſe; for graffes ſo let, fall out anon, or be blowen out.</p>
            <p>Therefore loue yee the incitiue word, leſt ye loſe it vnawares, embrace it with all complacencie of affection, ſo ſhall no
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:17891:95"/> ſtorme ſtirre it, nor force amoue it; it is not enough to receiue the word, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye receiue the loue of the word; Shall not ſome be damned becauſe they receiued not the loue of the truth<note n="m" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.10.</note>? O how I loue thy laws<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 119.97.</note> ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> it is my meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the day, yea, day and night the exerciſe of the bleſſed man; it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed within him, it is in his heart, and loued with his heart, the heart as ſoone to be loſt as the word ingraffed therein, and incorporated;<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.8. Pſal. 51.6.</note> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the inward parts,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:17891:95"/> and hidden in the hidden part.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Bound faſt and clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed about the impe of the word inſerted; it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſepted and ſtrengthened, yea, (as an orchard or vineyard with wals and hedges) fenced and forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with holy cares, and godly iealouſies, leſt wilde and harmefull beaſts breake it off, or bite it off, or come nigh it to hurt it. How many caueats hath the Apoſtle in his Epiſtles to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; <hi>Deceiue not your ſelues; Be not deceiued</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9 Gal. 6.7.</note>; <hi>Let no man deceiue you with
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:17891:96"/> vaine words,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.6.</note>; <hi>Let no man beguile you with inticing words; Let no man ſpoile you through Philoſophie and vaine deceit after the tradition of men, or after the rudiments of the world</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">2 Coloſſ. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. Beſides, the beaſts of <hi>Epheſus</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.32.</note>, and the grieuous wolues<note n="x" place="margin">Act. 20.29.</note>, what care tooke he to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect and defeat, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent and preuince<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Prauin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cire</hi> Gal. 2.5.</note>, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning the truth, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugning the aduerſaries, not giuing to them place by ſubiection, no not for an houre, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell ſtabliſhed might continue for euer. Let
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:17891:96"/> the ſame minde be in you which was alſo in him. The word ingraffed hedge yee about, fence and keepe ſafe from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant perſons, euill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, cares, riches, the pleaſures of this life, vnbeleefe, Apoſtaſie, and ſuch like. The enuious man will (if he can) make a breach vpon it, and bring in theſe deſtroyers; Therefore take yee heed, yea, let him that thinketh he ſtandeth<note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>11, 12,</note> take heed leſt he fall, or bee ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in an houre that hee knoweth not.</p>
            <p>Finally, fruit is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:17891:97"/> to bee had vnto holineſſe, and the end euerlaſting life<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 6.22.</note>. Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and winter the plant the ſame, fat in old age, and flouriſhing as the Palme tree, not blaſted with the winds of other vaine doctrines, not nip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with the froſts of hearts hardneſſe, or na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures remiſſeneſſe; not beaten downe by the meſſengers of Satan, buffeting the branches, nor withered ſo much as in one leafe, with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of the times, but as thoſe that be plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 92.13.</note> in the houſe of the
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:17891:97"/> Lord, (the<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> increaſe giuen of God) fruitfull in old age, and comfortfull in affliction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let a man therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelfe, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren proue your ſelues,</hi> whether yee haue or no the comforting word, which is the ingraffed word. The heart vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, inciſion not made for inſition, no ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted nor cloſed about with louing affection, no ſenſure about it, nor any fruit appearing, it is not ingraffed, nor affordeth it refreſhment to the ſoule that is wearie: But
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:17891:98"/> the heart cleane through the word which is ſpoken, inciſion made, the impe ſetled and cloſed on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide with embrace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of loue, fenced and fruitfull, it is ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed, and THE WORD, which is <hi>comfort in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remaineth what is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, <hi>De ratione conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landi,</hi> how and in what manner the poore affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted are comforted by the word. In <hi>Iſay</hi> 30.21. it is ſaid; <hi>Thine eare ſhall heare a word behinde thee ſaying, This is the way,</hi> &amp;c.<note n="d" place="margin">Emphaticè verbum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendi poni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: Deum hic padago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge comparat, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pueret ſibi ante oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culas ſtatuit, &amp;c. Marlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t. in loc.</note> As pupils from behinde
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:17891:98"/> them heare the voice of their Schoolemaſter or Tutor teaching and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhing them, ſo the ſeruants of the Lord his heauenly-voice, and in their affliction they are (by the word <hi>mixed with faith incordiated, hid in the heart,</hi> inſcribed and ingraffed) informed and comforted as here fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>By the word through faith, they vnderſtand,</hi> That afflictions are ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Gods decree, which is ſealed, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſure as<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 125.1.</note> Mount Sion, not to be remoued;
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:17891:99"/> fals a ſparrow to the ground<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 10.29.</note>, or an haire from the head without him? The ſufferings of the Saints are fore-ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as themſelues fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 8.29.</note>. Thus when I remember, I powre out in mee my ſoule thus<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal 42.4.</note>: Hath God decreed to me, and appointed mee to beare the euill vpon me? I will without any reluctation beare it, the ſtiffe-necked ſtriue with the yoke to their hurt; it is good to yeeld in youth<note n="h" place="margin">Lam. 3.27.</note>, in the firſt houre, in the laſt all muſt. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <hi>Shimei</hi> curſe mee? The
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:17891:99"/> Lord hath bidden him<note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 16.10.</note>: Doth <hi>Saul</hi> perſecute me? Vexed he is with an euill ſpirit ſent from the Lord<note n="k" place="margin">1 Sam. 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9.</note>: Doe other men, vnreaſonable and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, inſedable and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, inſeſt, oppoſe, plot againſt me, thruſt ſore at me, that I might fall, and fal into the pit which they haue digged for me<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 3.1.</note>? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they are (as <hi>Paul</hi> of the <hi>Galatians</hi>) mad men, diſtracted in their minds, they know not what they doe; what<note n="m" place="margin">Io. 8.44.</note> doe they but the luſts of the deuill? What are they but his agents and inſtruments?
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:17891:100"/> yet permitted all of my Lord &amp; my God to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me, &amp; to proue me<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 8.2.</note>, &amp; to know what is in me; whether I wil truſt in him, &amp; cleaue to him; or<note n="*" place="margin">Tentatio probatio in, non perditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis.</note>, it is a tentation of probation, not of deſtruction. Doth ſickneſſe afflict me? it is the ſeruant of the Lord comming and going as the Centurions<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 8.8, 9.</note> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his word. Doth any preſſure or other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſter ingrauate or grieue me? nothing happeneth or is done, nor ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen or bee done vnto me, but what the hand of God and his counſell
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:17891:100"/> hath before determined to be done<note n="p" place="margin">Act. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. Therefore being vile in mine owne eyes, and baſe in mine owne ſight<note n="q" place="margin">2 Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22.</note>; I ſay as he that went vp barefoot by the aſcent of Mount <hi>Oliuert</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">2 Sam. 15 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</note>; Behold, here I am, let the Lord doe to me as ſeemeth good vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. Surely hee will not caſt off for euer, but though hee cauſe griefe<note n="ſ" place="margin">Lam. 3, 32,</note>, yet will he haue compaſſion; and <hi>This is my comfort in my affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>By the word through faith they vnderſtand,</hi> That afflictions are argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the adoption
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:17891:101"/> of ſonnes vnto God<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 12.6.</note>, euery ſonne whom hee receiueth, <hi>flagellat,</hi> hee ſcourgeth, yet not in his anger, but with iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to teach them his iudgements. Impunity a note of baſtardy, yea, ſaith the ſpirit<note n="u" place="margin">Verſe 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>, if ye be without chaſtiſement, whereof all are partakers, then are ye baſtards and not ſonnes. Baſtards may eſcape that increpation, correction, diſcipline, &amp; nurture, which ſons muſt ſuffer: many vile ſeruants haue much more liberty and mony in their purſe, than many dears chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            <pb n="191" facs="tcp:17891:101"/>
            <p>The naturall ſonne, a bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e prepared him, had his eares bored and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as other mens, <hi>Iſay</hi> 50.6.<note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 50.6.</note>. A man of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, and acquainted with griefes<note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 53.3.</note>, tempted himſelfe<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 2. vlt.</note>, buffeted and ſmitten, yet not rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, neither turned hee away his, backe from the ſmiters, nor his face from ſhame and ſpitting. The adoptiue ſonnes (when they are chaſtened with paine vpon their bed,<note n="a" place="margin">Iob 33.19, 20, 21, 22.</note> and the multitude of their bones with ſtrong paine, when their life ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horreth bread, and their
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:17891:102"/> ſoule dainty meat, when their fleſh is conſumed away, and their bones ſticke out, when their ſoule draweth neare to the graue, and their life to the deſtroyer) haue alſo their inſtructions ſealed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I remember I powre out in me my ſoule thus;</hi> Wherefore ſhould I feare in the dayes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 49.5.</note>, when puniſhment or death, the iniquity of my heeles compaſſe mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, it is at the worſt but a bruiſe in the heele. The ſerpents head is broken, and the hunters ſnare:
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:17891:102"/> I ſee my ſelfe now ſaued from wrath, of which I was by nature the child<note n="c" place="margin">Eph. 2.3.</note>. The childe of God I am adopted, I know it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe chaſtened, I endure the chaſtiſement. A ſon without controuerſie, of a truth I perceiue it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I forget not the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horation which ſpeaketh vnto me, as vnto a ſonne.</p>
            <p>My ſonne, deſpiſe not thou the chaſtening of the Lord, neither be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of his correction, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther faint when thou art rebuked of him; for whom the Lord loueth, hee correcteth and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth,
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:17891:103"/> euen as a father the ſonne in whom hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth.<note place="margin">Pro. 3.11. and Heb. 12.5, 6. compared.</note> A deare ſon I am<note n="d" place="margin">Ier. 31.19, 10.</note>, I am a pleaſant childe, my father which is in heauen taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in nice; his bowels found and are troubled for mee; ſurely hee will haue mercie on me aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of my ſelfe; ſurely, hee will delight himſelfe in mee: confounded in my ſelfe, for that I beare the reproach of my youth. Therefore I will, whatſoeuer things I ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, delight my ſelfe in him. This ſhall ſwallow vp my griefes, this ſhall
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:17891:103"/> giue, or cauſe to bee gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto mee the deſires of my heart<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7.4.</note>, this the ſtrength of my life. This the ſtrong conſolation; and this is my comfort in my affliction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>By the word through faith they vnderſtand:</hi> That afflictions are eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of the brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in Chriſt, of confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie to him, of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him, the luſtre of his image, and the markes thereof, the marks of the Lord Ieſus in his members, yea the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of Chriſt<note n="f" place="margin">Phil. 3.10</note>, and on the whole bodie, which is
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:17891:104"/> called Chriſt<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12.</note>, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in the brethren which are in the world<note n="h" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.13.</note>, and reflected on him, who is not aſhamed to call them, that ſuffering are ſanctified, <hi>brethren</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 2.11.</note>: Is not his care and ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy expreſſed?<note n="k" place="margin">Act. 9.4.</note> perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted hee is in them that beare his name, and his is their reproach:<note n="l" place="margin">Heb. 11.26.13.13.</note> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Chriſt called.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I remember, I powre out in me my ſoule thus.</hi> Why art thou caſt downe, ô my ſoule, and why art thou diſquieted within mee<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 42.5</note>. No bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then now on thee, that is
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:17891:104"/> not now on the brethren abroad. The ſame affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.9.</note>, the ſame alſo the ſufferings of Chriſt; not a teare ſheddeſt thou, which hee puts not into a bottle, not one ſigh from thy broken heart, which enters not into his open eares; not one gaſh on thee, of which his ſoule is not ſenſible; not one ſcratch or ſcarre in thy face, which appeares not in his; not one fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row on thy backe, which turnes not vpon his. A brother of low degree, yet brother to Ieſus Chriſt in the higheſt.</p>
            <pb n="198" facs="tcp:17891:105"/>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Iam. 1.9.</note>Reioyce therefore in that thou art exalted, and run with patience to the race which is ſet before thee, looking aſwell vnto Ieſus Chriſt the Author and finiſher of thy faith, thy faithfull brother and bearer of thy griefes,<note n="o" place="margin">Iſa. 53.4.</note> as alſo to the brethren en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>during the ſame croſſe, and deſpiſing the ſhame thereof in the world: If any draw backe<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 10.38.</note> whoſe ſoule ſhall haue any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in ſuch? Nothing hath taken thee, but that which is common,<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon the exinanition to them in the bodie, before
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:17891:105"/> the exaltation: and this is my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in my afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>By the word through faith they vnderſtand:</hi> That afflictions are to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of the preſence of God, going before his Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael out of Aegypt into Canaan<note n="r" place="margin">Deut 8.2, 3.</note>. Know yee not what hee did to humble them, as they went? Who knoweth not what the preſence of a father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt children doth? euen keepe them in awe, or not awefull rebukes are heard, and had ſtripes. The righteous are recompenced on the earth<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pro. 11.31</note>, ſometimes by the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:17891:106"/> wicked and ſinner, <hi>The hand of the Lord, and the ſword in his hand</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 17.4.</note>, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning euerie way (as the<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 3. vlt.</note> Cherubims flaming ſword) to keepe them whom hee keepes in the way euerlaſting. Theſe recompenced alſo as they behaue themſelues ill in their doings. <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lekites their end to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed for euer</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Num. 24.20.</note>. But <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> not ſmitten<note n="x" place="margin">Iſa. 27.7.</note> as the ſmiters of <hi>Iacob,</hi> nor ſlaine according to the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his aduerſaries o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerturned, ouerturned, ouerturned with an ah<note n="y" place="margin">Iſa. 1.24.</note>, and damned as Sodom<note n="z" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.6.</note>
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:17891:106"/> with an ouerthrow. The Lords portion<note n="a" place="margin">Deut. 32.9.</note> is his people, and theirs his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries.<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 33.14.</note> His preſence is alwaies with them, and ſhall bee to day as yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and ſo for euer. Might I, with your fauor, change my voice, I might ſhew you a myſterie to be admired of you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the Lord is, ſo is his Iſrael, and as they are, ſo is he in the world</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Io. 4.17.</hi> Nulla eſt in mundo miſeria aut afflictio in quam Deus non reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat, &amp;c. Fonſec. Sab<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ante Dom. Quadra.</note> Hearing their cries, and ſeeing their iniuries, he manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted himſelfe not as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire, but as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning buſh, as confined himſelfe within a buſh,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:17891:107"/> his people ſtraitened in the confines of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> and they offended as burning himſelfe, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his ſoule for their miſerie, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 10.16. and afflicted himſelfe in all their afflictions, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.9. Although hee ſpeake ſharply, and deale rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with them, yet he ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly remembers them, <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.19. and will ſaue them from their enemies, from the hands of them that hate them, from ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of pots, from the iron yoke, from the heat of the fornace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I remember, I
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:17891:107"/> powre out in me my ſoule thus:</hi> Doth the Lord beat me with his rod, and ſtrike me with his fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffe, his rod and his ſtaffe both comfort me<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 23.4</note>; His hand not farre off, nor his preſence from me, but at hand, and with mee, to deliuer me: Infirmities, reproaches, neceſſities, diſtreſſes enuiron me, yet trembling, and not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, not reſiſting, nor rebelling againſt him that is with mee; as hee in me, I may take pleaſure in them<note n="e" place="margin">Iſa. 25.4.</note>; Ths Lord is with me, a mightie terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble one, a ſtrength to mee
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:17891:108"/> poore, a ſtrength to mee needy in my diſtreſſe, a refuge from the ſtorme, a ſhadow from the heat, when the blaſt of the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible ones is as a ſtorme againſt the wall<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.8, 9.</note> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled I am on euerie ſide, yet not diſtreſſed; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, yet not in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire, or not altogether deſtitute of meanes; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, yet not forſaken; caſt downe, yet not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed; when I fall, I ſhall ariſe, when I ſit in darkneſſe, the Lord is a light vnto me<note n="g" place="margin">Micah<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7.8.</note>; when I am impleaded, hee ſhall plead my cauſe, when I
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:17891:108"/> am iudged, and in the hands of the wicked, hee will not leaue mee<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 37.33.</note> but execute iudgement for me: when I am ſifted of Satan as wheat, hee will confirme my faith<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.8.</note>: when I am caſt downe hee will comfort me.<note n="k" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.6.</note> Gratious hee is, I know, and am perſwaded, that hee will performe all things for me<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 57.2, 3.</note>, yea ſend from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, all helpes on earth failing, and ſaue me from them that would ſwallow me vp. Therefore I caſt my ſelfe on him, I roll, I commit my way vnto him<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 37.5, &amp;c.</note> Hee ſhall bring it
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:17891:109"/> to paſſe, my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as the light, and my iudgement as the noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, my refuge is vnder the ſhadow of his wings, vntill theſe calamities ſhall bee ouerpaſt<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 57.1</note>, my rocke he is, my fortreſſe, my deliuer<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 18.1</note>, my buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, my high Tower, my God, and his preſence the horne of my ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And this is my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in my affliction.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By the word through faith they vnderſtand: That afflictions are the <hi>high way vnto heauen</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Act. 14.12.</note>, no walking on pillowes thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but on thornes and
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:17891:109"/> ſtones, the ſtrait gate not eaſily entred at, preſſing there is and muſt be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 11, 12.</note> or elſe no en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance there. In the broad way is elbow-roome, but thorow the ſtraits, as the bleſſed goe to the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting gates, are ſtrong oppoſitions by the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and powers, by the rulers of the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this world, and the wickedneſſes in the high places<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 6.12</note>.</p>
            <p>This when I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, I powre out in mee my ſoule thus: The world which now laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and reioyceth, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketha
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:17891:110"/> me, wretched man, to weepe and lament; yet is my ſorrow turned into ioy, yea I count it all ioy, when I fall into tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note n="t" place="margin">Iam. 1.2.</note>, I am exceeding ioyfull in all my tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.10.</note>; Are they not portalls before the houſe of God, and the gates of Heauen? Guides and markes they are in the ſtraight ſtreet, in the old way to the ſoules reſt, of the new and liuing way to perfection, the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of Ieſus Chriſt, made perfect he through ſufferings<note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 2.10</note>, and endured for the ioy that was ſet
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:17891:110"/> before him<note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 12.3</note>, ſuch oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſinners againſt himſelfe, as are written in the volume of the booke, ſo will I being confident of this verie thing, That the preſent preſſure is the way vnto peace in the after ends<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 37.37.</note>, the paines of Hell vnto the ioyes of Heauen, the reproaches of Chriſt to the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting pleaſures, the valley of the ſhadow of death, the path of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe vnto perfection: And this is my comfort in my affliction.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>By the word through
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:17891:111"/> faith they vnderſtand:</hi> That afflictions are the <hi>Porters,</hi> which open the doores of diſtreſſed ſoules, that the gratious promiſes may come in; what are the gracious promiſes of our God? Verily, to haue mercie on his afflicted, <hi>Iſay</hi> 49.13. according to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of his tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.32. to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them with great mercies, and to haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on them with euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kindneſſe, <hi>Iſay</hi> 54.7, 8. to bee with them in trouble, to deliuer them, and honour them, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
               <pb n="211" facs="tcp:17891:111"/> 91.15. yea, to bee with them for euer, euen vnto the end of the world, <hi>Matth. vlt. vlt.</hi> neuer to leaue them, neuer to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake them, <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 1.5. ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken firſt to that great Duke, but applyed by the ſpirit vnto the little flock of the little ones, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13.5. vnto the leaſt of the little ones that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues on Ieſus Chriſt, The Lord hath ſaid, I will neuer leaue thee nor forſake thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I rememher, I powre out in me my ſoule thus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 3.10.</note> By ſight I ſee how many liue not by faith,
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:17891:112"/> their barnes filled with plenty,<note place="margin">Luk, 12.19</note> and their preſſes burſting out with new wine, they ſing hearts caſe, and ſoule take thine caſe, but the bread of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, and water of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction or of oppreſſion giuen.<note place="margin">Heb. 11.13</note> The iuſt liue by faith, ſeeing the promiſe (as the fathers) afarre off, yet ſaluting them as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and embracing the ſame, as the verie ioy and reioycing of their heart. Therefore it is good for mee to reſt my ſelfe on, and in the promiſes of God;<note place="margin">Ier. 1.12.</note> for hee will haſten his word to performe it:
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:17891:112"/> his word he will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber vnto mee his ſeruant,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.149.</note> vpon which he hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mee to hope:<note place="margin">Heb. 10.35.</note> I will not caſt away my confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which hath great recompence of reward, patience in me ſhall haue her perfect worke,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.4.</note> that I may bee perfect and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, wanting nothing. I will doe the will of God, that I may receiue the promiſe, yet a little while and hee that ſhall come,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.37.</note> will come, and will not tarrie, euen the God of all grace in a time accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then ſhall my light breake forth as the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:17891:113"/> and mine health ſhall ſpring forth ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly;<note place="margin">Iſa. 58.8.10.</note> the day-ſpring from on high ſhall viſit mee: I ſhall ſee in that day,<note place="margin">Hab. 2.3.</note> the word in the worke. The viſion is yet for an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, but at the end it ſhall ſpeake, and not lye, though it tarrie, I will wait for it, becauſe it will ſurely come with refection: And this is my comfort in my affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>7. <hi>By the word through faith they vnderſtand:</hi> That affliction haue with them power from bone, preſeruatiue and
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:17891:113" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſanatiue, had not <hi>Ionah</hi> beene ſwallowed of the Whale, he had beene of the ſea; and Betheſda's poole healed, when trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled: <hi>Happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the man whom God errecteth, Iob</hi> 5.17. This happineſſe who can declare? not one, not knowen, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with a floud, what gulph is eſcaped, who knoweth? or what malady cured, ſome mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie endured.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I remember, I powre cut in mee my ſoule thus:</hi> The ſmarting rod vpon mee, may bee a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting ſtaffe vnto mee,
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:17891:114"/> without it I might fall into a fouler ditch. Had not it, a worſe thing might haue happened vnto me: Phyſick makes ſicke before whole, a time of health for this trouble will come, and I will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it. Behold, my Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian ſtandeth before the doore, hee looketh vpon mee, and mee hee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa. 66.3.</hi> Vt curent ſpaſmum medici pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curent fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brim.</note>. This ague to ſhake me, he doth procure mee to cure a more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conuulſion in mee: or as <hi>Lot</hi> was in Sodome, I may bee in this world,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.6.</note> and theſe troubles (as the Angels on him) lay hold
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:17891:114"/> on mee, the Lord being mercifull vnto mee to bring me forth, and to ſet me without the bounds of deſtruction: I will therefore take in all that come, for in doing this (as other in their tents) I may entertaine, in this earthly tabernacle, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels vnawares.<note place="margin">Heb. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> An An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell ſent from God, for ſome ſpeciall good to me, is my tribulation, and this is my comfort in my affliction.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>By the word through faith they vnderſtand:</hi> That afflictions demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate faithfull and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:17891:115"/> branches. Euerie branch of the vine that beareth fruit is purged, that it may bring forth more fruit.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Io. 15.2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, defractio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riantium. Aret. in loc. Fert vberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum poſt refectionem. Aret. vbi ſup. Vitis fodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur, ſterce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatur aliiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que multis exercetur laboribus, &amp;c. Aret. vbi ſup.</note> For as after the refection &amp; defracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the parts luxuriant, the branches of the vine yeeld more fruit, ſo the faithfull in their afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (which are as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or ruſticke purgations) are the more fruitfull, not pruned at eaſe, and grow wilde apace, or their grapes wilde, but pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged afflicted, wounded within and bruiſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, euerie gift is ſtirred vp, and ſet to work euery
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:17891:115"/> grace that is in them; the lights put vnder a buſhell before, ſhine afterwards as in candleſtickes ſet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hills. What vſe before of faith, or of patience? before, what hope or ioy in the holy Ghoſt? As the wine forced runs out of the preſſe, and as the weights of a clocke turne all the wheeles about, ſo the loads of afflictions preſſe out of them that are Chriſts, the praiſes of Chriſt<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.9.</note>, and ſhew forth the hidden vertues of them that are the hidden ones of God<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 83.4.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I remember
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:17891:116"/> I powre out in me my ſoule thus:</hi> Pinched I am, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and pared nigh, yea, cut to the quicke, that I bleed in ſpirit; but needfull the compuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it is the firſt degree of inward humiliation; if a wound bee, it is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and not hurtfull; nor the third, which is the contrition it ſelfe. Better is a conſcience wounded,<note place="margin">D. Slater: Salue for a woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſpirit.</note> than a conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſeared; better a heart grownd to powder with the millſtone of wrath turning about vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, than one dedolent, and paſt feeling of ſin and
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:17891:116"/> wrath; better a ſoule to be lopped in the paſſions of ſinnes, than to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted with ranke luſts, or neglected and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected. Not meerely poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall the wounded ſpirit in the children of God, as in <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> the beginning of their hell, but either caſtigatory for the chaſtiſement of ſome particular diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, as <hi>Dauids,</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batory for triall, as <hi>Iobs,</hi> or percurſory for preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>Pauls</hi> thorne in his fleſh, leſt through the abundance of reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he ſhould be exalted
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:17891:117"/> aboue meaſure,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 12.</note> or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, for the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of vncleane and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill thoughts, imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and reaſonings, touching Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the word, the profeſſion, the power of nature, ſelfe-abilitie to conuert, inherent righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, good works, freewill, and ſecurity in the arme of fleſh. How ſuch ſparkles riſe in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwept chimneyes, the fire blowne with the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of hell, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that knoweth the deuices of Satan?<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> Therefore I will through
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:17891:117"/> him that worketh the will and the good deed, giue all diligence to ſearch and try mine own wayes. In euery crooked way I may finde a croſſe,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> my croſſes indigitate mine exorbitancies: As I deprehend them, I will amend them, and bring forth fruit meet for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, new obedience in all things, the old things in mee ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all new. When I ſhoot forth,<note place="margin">Iſai. 27.8.</note> the Lord will in meaſure debate with mee, and ſtay the rough wind, in the day of the Eaſt wind, when I
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:17891:118"/> bloſſome and bud, and fill the face of the world with fruit in its ſeaſon: for I will approue my ſelfe as the ſeruant of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 6.5, 6.</note> in much patience in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes, in tumults, in labours by the word of truth, by the power of God, by the armour of righteouſneſſe on the right hand, and on the left; by honour and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, by good report and euill report, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted, yet not profli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, as chaſtened, and yet not killed, as ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and yet reioycing,
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:17891:118"/> as pruned being pampi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, too full of needleſſe ſprigges, and ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous twigges, yet not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away as the fruitleſſe branch, nor caſt forth, nor withered, nor gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of men, nor caſt into the fire, but purged for fructification:<note place="margin">Io. 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>and this is my comfort in my affliction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>By the word of God through faith, they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,</hi> that afflictions are <hi>neceſſary exerciſes, Heb.</hi> 12.13. a kind of wreſtling betweene the Lord and his ſeruants. Troubles on them, his hands on them, and theirs on him, the
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:17891:119"/> right hand of faith.<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.5.</note> Thus it is wreſted, and who preuaileth? Alwayes the afflicted, ſtriuing lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. The lawfull ſtriuing learned of <hi>Iacob, Hoſeah</hi> his interpreter, hee had power with God, and preuailed, for hee wept, and made ſupplication vnto him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11. ſo may all ouercome, if the Lord may ouercome; the heart yeelded vp, the ſtrife is ended, humbled in the ſight of God, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately lifted vp, <hi>Iam.</hi> 5.10. teares ſeene, hee yeelds, ſupplications made, he takes away his
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:17891:119"/> hand; the victory with facility had; grieuous the conflict for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time, yet ioyous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards;<note place="margin">Heb. 12.11.</note> the Lord not let goe, the bleſſing not obtained.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I remember I powre out in me my ſoule thus:</hi> Is the euill vpon me, the hand of the Lord, Doth hee thereby wreſtle with mee, wretched man that I am, who ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mee?<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> Hee will him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hold mee downe with his left, and vphold mee with his owne right hand; my faith his gift;<note place="margin">Io. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> his worke that I beleeue
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:17891:120"/> in him, beleeuing in him I cannot, nor ſhall be caſt downe of him, or out of his ſight,<note place="margin">Gen. 35.25</note> touched happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the hollow of my thigh, as hee wreſtleth with mee, it may ſlip out of ioynt, or the ſinew may ſhrinke, and I may halt vpon it, but my faith ſhall not faile. Therefore will I, while the Lord with mee, ſtriue lawfully with him, holding my ſelfe faſt by him, weeping before him, and making inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſupplications vnto him: exerciſed this ſhall bee my exerciſe vntill I preuaile, and through
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:17891:120"/> him, I ſhall preuaile with him, he will hold me faſt, ſee my teares,<note place="margin">Pſal. 6.8.</note> heare the voyce of my weeping;<note place="margin">Iſai. 38.5.</note> giue mee the petitions that I deſire of him, bleſſe me with the new name,<note place="margin">Reuel. 2.17.</note> in the white ſtone giuen to him that ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, I ſhall haue prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly power with God and men.<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.6.</note> I will not feare what men can doe vnto mee, aduantagious the diſaduantage, the agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion requiſite, lucratiue the luctuation: And this is my comfort in my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>By the word
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:17891:121"/> through faith they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand:</hi> That afflictions precede the ioy of the Lord, and glorie to come, as the pleaſures of ſinne, deſtruction and damnation. To them that make their bellies their Gods,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note> and that minde earthly things, as the enemies of the croſſe of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Rom. 29, 10.</note> 
               <hi>Tribulation and anguiſh, indignation and wrath;</hi> but to them that lye amongſt the pots, in ſtocks, in the dungeon, in the briars and in the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning buſhes, induring the fierie triall of their faith, <hi>fulneſſe of ioy and bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:17891:121"/> of glorie,</hi> the triall of their faith being much more pretious than of gold which periſheth, though it bee tried in the fire, ſhall bee found vnto praiſe, and honour, and glorie, at the appearing of Ieſus Chriſt. The Paſſouer of the <hi>great</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Reuel. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation</hi> celebrated, or the ſame paſſed ouer, they ſhall waſh their robes,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.21.</note> and make them white in the bloud of the Lambe, their vile bodies alſo be faſhioned like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the glorious bodie of Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall ſhine as the firmament, yea as the
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:17891:122"/> Sun in the height of his glorie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This when I remember, I powre out in me my ſoule thus:</hi> Of a truth I perceiue,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.18.</note> that the ſufferings of the preſent time are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to bee compared to the glorie which ſhall be reuealed in me, I reckon not the temporall euill, but haue reſpect to the eternall good: I faint not,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.16, 17.</note> for though mine out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man periſh, mine inward is renewed day by day, my light afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, worketh for mee a far more exceeding and
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:17891:122"/> eternall weight of glorie. Therefore vnder my preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.10.</note> I will by patient continuance in well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeeke for glorie, and honour, and immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and eternall life; for I am perſwaded, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tribulation, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, nor perſecution; nor famine,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> nor naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor perill, nor ſword, nor death, nor life, nor Angels, nor princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palities, nor powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor any other creature, ſhall be able to preuent the ioy, or to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:17891:123"/> me from the glorie to come, the ſpirit of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie reſteth already on me, and full is my heart of ioy in the Holy Ghoſt. The God of all grace hath by Chriſt Ieſus called me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his eternall glorie, and after that I haue ſuffered a while,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.10.</note> will cauſe mee to enter into his ioy, which is fulneſſe of ioy, and crowne mee with his glorie, which is eternall glorie. To him be glorie and dominion, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17891:123"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
